<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Mirabilis annus secundus, or, The second part of the second years prodigies being a true additional collection of many strange signs and apparitions which have this last year been seen in the heavens, and in the earth, and in the waters : together with many remarkable accidents and signal judgments which have befel divers persons who have apostatized from the truth, and have been persecutors of the Lord's faithful servants : published as a warning to all, speedily to repent, and to meet the Lord in the way of His judgments.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 146KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 31 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A50974</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12185282</idno>
  <idno type="VID">55733</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240961193</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing M2204</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R2035</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">12185282</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A50974)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 55733)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 610:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Mirabilis annus secundus, or, The second part of the second years prodigies being a true additional collection of many strange signs and apparitions which have this last year been seen in the heavens, and in the earth, and in the waters : together with many remarkable accidents and signal judgments which have befel divers persons who have apostatized from the truth, and have been persecutors of the Lord's faithful servants : published as a warning to all, speedily to repent, and to meet the Lord in the way of His judgments.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 53, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1662.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Omens.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-06 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>Maria Cecilia Caride </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>Maria Cecilia Caride</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:55733:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:55733:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>MIRABILIS ANNUS SECUNDUS:</hi> OR, THE SECOND PART Of the SECOND YEARS PRODIGIES.</p>
            <p>Being a true Additional <hi>Collection</hi> of many strange SIGNS and APPARITIONS, which have this last Year been seen in the HEAVENS, and in the EARTH, and in the WATERS.</p>
            <p>Together with many remarkable <hi>Accidents,</hi> and signal <hi>Judgments</hi> which have befel divers Persons who have Aposta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized from the Truth, and have been Persecutors of the Lord's faithful Servants.</p>
            <p>Published as a Warning to all, speedily to Repent, and to meet the Lord in the way of his Judgments.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <bibl>Psal. 65.5.</bibl>
                  <hi>By terrible things in Righteousness wilt thou answer us, O God of our Salvation, who art the Confidence of all the ends of the Earth, and of them that are afar off upon the Sea.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <bibl>Luk. 17.32.</bibl>
                  <hi>Remember Lot's Wife.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Prodigia sunt Signa Divinae Admonitionis ut excitemur ad timorem Dei, et Caveamus per resipiscentiam futura in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commoda. <bibl>
                     <hi>Brentius.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
               <p>Ipsis (<hi>viz.</hi> Signis &amp; Portentis) vere pii se Consolantur quia sciunt sibi illa in Bonum cooperatura, deinde laetantur quia illa sciunt esse Patris sui Exercitum. <bibl>
                     <hi>Pet. Mart.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>Printed in the Year, 1662.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:55733:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:55733:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>HAving at length, through the assistance of Providence, overcome the many interruptions which have attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the <hi>Press,</hi> we have (though much later than we promised, and indeed intended) at last Mid-wifed into the World a <hi>Second Part</hi> of this years <hi>Prodigies.</hi> The particulars whereof we hope, will answer the Character we gave of them in the <hi>First Part,</hi> and appear to all <hi>impartial</hi> Perusers as <hi>remarkable</hi> and <hi>considerable</hi> as any, which we have hitherto acquainted the World with.</p>
            <p>God's Warnings we see do croud in very fast upon us, and the throws of Providence come extream thick: Certainly there is some <hi>great thing</hi> at the Birth,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Isa.</hi> 28.21.</note>
               <hi>and the Lord is rising from his Place to do his Work, even his strange Work.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And let all the World know, that God is now by these things, fulfilling his Word: For there is a great proportion, and sweet Analogy between the Word and Works of God; What are his most strange &amp; wonderful Works, but his Word fulfilled and accomplished? according to that of the <hi>Psalmist,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Psalm</hi> 148.8.</note>
               <hi>Fire and Hail, Snow and Vapour, stormy Wind fulfilling his Word.</hi> These, and other such like Prodigies are the most certain and infallible Commentaries upon the word of Threatning, and the word of Promise recorded in the Scriptures; and had we but the wisdom to bring the Word and Works of God toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, what a sweet Harmony should we see between them? Which, as it is very terrible to the Wicked, so is matter of great rejoycing and triumphing to the Godly, who see the Scriptures fulfilled in that peculiar favour which the Lord vouchsafes to them, in saving them by <hi>Signs and Wonders.</hi> So that it may be said to the <hi>Generation of the Righteous,</hi> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Moses</hi> spake to the <hi>Israelites,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 4.34. <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.36.</note>
               <hi>Hath God assayed to go and take him a Nation from the midst of another Nation by Temptations, by Signs and by Wonders, &amp;c?</hi> For, (as <hi>Moses</hi> expresses it) <hi>The Lord seeth that the Power of his People is gone, and there is none shut up
<pb facs="tcp:55733:3"/> or left,</hi> therefore he will immediately plead their Cause him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self. And truly he hath done it <hi>wonderfully</hi> this year; how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny remarkable Judgments hath he executed with his own im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate Hand upon the Enemies of his People, whereof the ensuing Narrative give a very true and impartial account? Insomuch that we may say, it hath been with us as it was for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly in <hi>Bohemia,</hi> God's Judgments were so many, and so frequent upon the Enemies of the <hi>Bohemian</hi> Professors, that it was often used as a <hi>Proverb</hi> amongst the <hi>Adversaries</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bohem.</hi> Hist. <hi>p.</hi> 76.</note>
               <hi>If any man be weary of his life, let him but attempt some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing against the Piccardines</hi> (for so were the most zealous and spiritual Servants of Christ then called) <hi>and he shall not out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live a year.</hi> The Lord hath made good his Word by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, <hi>Behold, I will make Jerusalem a Cup of Trembling unto all the People round about,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Zech.</hi> 12.2, 3.</note>
               <hi>when they shall be in the Siege both against Judah and against Jerusalem: And in that day will I make Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>salem a burdensome Stone for all People, all that burden themselves with it, shall be cut in pieces, though all the People of the Earth be gathered together against it.</hi> Is it not Jesus Christ himself a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst whom these men engage? and wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> can be the issue of that, but disappointment and destruction? for as Christ is <hi>Piorum Rupes,</hi> a Rock of Refuge to his People; so he is <hi>Reo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum Scopulus,</hi> a Rock of Revenge to Persecutors to split them in pieces.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Judg.</hi> 6.21. <hi>Zech.</hi> 1.14. <hi>Deut.</hi> 32 22. <hi>Mat.</hi> 27 19.</note> Such a Rock as that out of which <hi>fire arose,</hi> even <hi>the fire of God's jealousie which burneth to the lowest Hell.</hi> Oh therefore, let them hearken to the Admonition which the Wife of <hi>Pilat</hi> gave to her Husband when he was about to give Judgment against Christ, <hi>Have thou nothing to do with that Just man.</hi> Let them do as <hi>Tertullian</hi> counselled <hi>Scapula, Si non nobis Tibi, si non Tibi Carthagini parcas.</hi> As men there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore love <hi>themselves</hi> or their <hi>Country,</hi> let them hearken to <hi>Gamaliels</hi> advice, and <hi>refrain from these men and let them alone; for if this Counsel or Work be of men,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 5.38, 39.</note>
               <hi>it will come to nought; but if it be of God, ye cannot over thro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> it, lest haply ye be found to fight against God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But amongst all the Defections and Prevarications of this day, none like those which are found amongst the <hi>Runegadoes:</hi> who in the face of the Sun, against all Principles of <hi>Light, Conscience,</hi> and <hi>Ingenuity,</hi> have received the mark of the <hi>Beast,</hi> at least in their <hi>right hands,</hi> if not in their <hi>foreheads</hi> also: they have most shamefully disserted their <hi>Colours,</hi> as the Apostle's
<pb facs="tcp:55733:3"/> phrase is. Some of them,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.38. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> while they have exhorted others to put on the whole Armour of God, have been found naked and destitute thereof themselves, and so like Cowards for meer fear, have with the <hi>Camelion,</hi> turned into all the Colours of the <hi>Rainbow.</hi> Others, <hi>Demas</hi>-like, for love of this present World, have relinquished the spiritual Ministry, and are turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be little less than <hi>Idolatrous Priests,</hi> as History reports <hi>Demas</hi> was at <hi>Thessalonica.</hi> These men steer the Course of their Religion only by the Compass of <hi>gain</hi> and <hi>profit;</hi> and as <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>novius</hi> says, <hi>Ubi non vident quaestum rident Christum.</hi> If the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferments be amongst the <hi>Non-Conformists,</hi> they will be <hi>Zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lots</hi> of that <hi>Faction:</hi> but if the most <hi>ridiculous, exploded</hi> and <hi>ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solete</hi> superstitious Fopperies, be the way to wordly advantage, they can cry as <hi>earnestly</hi> and as <hi>loud</hi> as any,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 19.34.</note>
               <hi>Great is Diana of the Ephesians.</hi> They follow Christ upon <hi>Judas</hi> his terms, but, <hi>Usque ad Loculorum officium,</hi> as <hi>Tertullians</hi> phrase is. They are like the <hi>Samaritans,</hi> who would claim Kindred with the <hi>Jews</hi> alwayes when they were in <hi>prosperity,</hi> but when they were in a <hi>suffering condition</hi> then they <hi>knew them not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But it is much to be feared that these men who have thus <hi>gone forth from us, were indeed never of us;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.19.</note> they began in Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrisie, and so must needs end in Apostasie: and whatever their professions or pretences have been in regard <hi>they have thus turned aside into their own crooked wayes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ps.</hi> 125.5.</note>
               <hi>the Lord</hi> (according as he hath threatned) <hi>shall lead them forth with the workers of Iniquity, but peace shall be upon Israel.</hi> Several most <hi>pregnant</hi> Instances of Gods making good that threatning against many of <hi>this years Back-sliders,</hi> the Reader is furnished with out of the <hi>last Part,</hi> as well of the <hi>former</hi> as of this <hi>present Collection,</hi> in which there is an Account given of some of the Lord's most sharp and terrible Dispensations towards the Apostates of this day, whom God hath dealt the more <hi>severely</hi> and <hi>exemplary</hi> with, because they have so <hi>impudently</hi> and <hi>audaciously</hi> abando<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned all former Professions,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.21, 22.</note> and <hi>have returned with the Dog to the vomit, and with the Sow that was washed, to their wallowing in the mire again,</hi> and so <hi>their latter end is worse than their begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. It had been much better for them they had never known the way of Righteousness, than after they have known it, to turn from the holy Commandment delivered unto them. Nocuit sane Judae fuisse Apostolum, &amp; Juliano Christianum,</hi> it was <hi>Judas</hi> his misery that he was an <hi>Apostle,</hi> and <hi>Julians</hi> that he was a <hi>Christian.</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:55733:4"/> The Condition of these men is much the <hi>worse,</hi> because they themselves seemed once to be so <hi>Good.</hi> By whom was <hi>Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian</hi> Reformation more promoted, the Covenant adored, and <hi>Meroz</hi> cursed, than by some of our present <hi>drunken Deans,</hi> with others, of an inferious rank, amongst the <hi>New-Conformists?</hi> who (as a Generation past all shame) have <hi>builded again the things which they once destroyed, and destroyed again the things which with hands lifted up to the most high God, they seemed once to build;</hi> and so have thereby made them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves the greater <hi>Transgressors.</hi> Upon which account the Lord hath made several of them very <hi>publick</hi> and <hi>eminent Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples</hi> of his <hi>sore displeasure,</hi> and hath set them up as so many <hi>Sea-marks,</hi> that the rest of their <hi>Brethren,</hi> with all others, might <hi>see</hi> and <hi>fear,</hi> and avoid the Rock upon which these men were split, and so <hi>have made Shipwrack of Faith and of a good Conscience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let every one then, without <hi>prejudice,</hi> and in the <hi>fear</hi> of the Lord, read and consider these <hi>Examples,</hi> with the rest of the <hi>Great and Wonderful Works of God,</hi> recorded in the ensuing <hi>Narrative.</hi> There is not a <hi>Judgment</hi> here set down, but it is of the same nature with those two mentioned by our <hi>Saviour,</hi> (the <hi>one</hi> was,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 13 1, 2, 3, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Serm. <hi>in Luk.</hi> 13 5. p. 6. <hi>Isa.</hi> 1.5.</note>
               <hi>Pilat's mingling the blood of some Galileans with their Sacrifices:</hi> and the <hi>other</hi> was, the <hi>Tower of Shilo falling upon some Jews</hi>) which were (as Dr. <hi>Jackson</hi> well observes from the Context) <hi>Portenta &amp; Prodigia,</hi> that is peculiar <hi>Signs</hi> or <hi>forewarnings</hi> of <hi>greater Calamities</hi> to follow, in case men still persist in their <hi>Apostacy,</hi> and (as the Lord complains by the Prophet) <hi>do revolt more and more.</hi> Therefore to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, <hi>Lege Historiam ne fias Historia, lege Juditia ne fias ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplum Juditii:</hi> that thou thy self mayest not become a <hi>Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>story,</hi> read and lay to heart <hi>this History;</hi> and that thou mayest not become an example of God's Judgments, let the <hi>remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Judgments</hi> of God here presented before thee, as a in <hi>Mirrour,</hi> make deep impressions upon thy Soul, to engage thee <hi>not to partake of the sins</hi> of this Generation,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 18 4.</note>
               <hi>lest thou partake with them also of their plagues.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:55733:4"/>
            <head>Several PRODIGIES, with strange and ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifying APPARITIONS, seen in the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens, from the Month of <hi>June,</hi> to the Month of <hi>September,</hi> 1662.</head>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>I.</hi> The form of a white Cross, and a Man's head upon it, seen in the Heavens.</head>
               <p>ON the first day of <hi>June</hi> 1662, an honest discreet person, living about <hi>Grubstreet,</hi> being in his Garden, and looking toward the Clouds streight before him, there appeared in the Sky a very clear place, free from Clouds, where he saw very plainly, the exact form of a white Cross; and on the top of the uppermost part of the Cross, on the end of it, was placed the form of a very comely mans Head: His face was round and plump, of a very fresh colour, a picked beard, his hair pretty long and turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up at the ends; and as he looked on it for a very short space of time, it suddenly passed away. The Spectator himself affirms this, and hath given it under his hand.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>II.</hi> The form of a Red Gallows, a Troop of Horsmen, and a Company of Footmen, seen in the Air.</head>
               <p>Upon the next day, being the second of <hi>June,</hi> the same person, in the same place, looking up into the Heavens, did see hanging in the Air as very near him, the perfect form of a Gallows; the colour whereof was as red as blood: but on a sudden while he was behold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it, it vanished away; and immediately after there appeared march<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing toward the East, very plain to the sight, a great Troop of Horse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and after them a Company of Footmen in Red Coats: As he was thus beholding them with great trouble in his mind, there comes to him one of his Neighbours, who beheld some part of them with him; and as they were marching away, they both plainly saw drawn out of one of the Files, two Horsemen at a good distance from the Main-body, and from each other. They affirm it was so plain, as
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:55733:5"/> if two men on horseback had been by them. This came immediately from the Spectators themselves, who are persons of honesty and repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>III.</hi> Two Suns exceeding bright, seen together in the Heavens.</head>
               <p>Upon the 9th of <hi>June</hi> 1662, not far from <hi>Dorchester,</hi> about five of the clock in the afternoon, there appeared two Suns together in the Heavens. The false Sun was exceeding bright, and did send forth Rays as the other did: It seemed to be about an hour and half higher than the true Sun; but it set before it. This is confirmed by Letters from unquestionable hands, who informed themselves of the truth of it from the eye-witnesses themselves.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>IV.</hi> The Sun very much darkened for three dayes together.</head>
               <p>By Letters from persons of very good reputation it is certified, that on the 4th, 5th and 6th dayes of <hi>July</hi> (the Sky being very clear and free from Clouds) about <hi>Boston</hi> in the County of <hi>Lincoln,</hi> the Sun was very much obscured and darkened, so that even at noon the people could behold it without the least offence to their eyesight. Several credible persons in those parts, who were Spectators, do daily testifie the truth of it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>V.</hi> First two, and then four Suns seen together in the Firmament, and in the midst of them a flaming Sword ascending.</head>
               <p>Also, at the place last mentioned, and on each of the same three dayes, at one and the same time of the day, the Sun did seem to divide it self, first, into two, and then into four Suns; and in the midst of them there was the form of a flaming Sword ascending. The Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctators, who are many, do affirm this as a thing most certainly true.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>VI.</hi> The form of a Man standing by the Sun, and a multitude of Mens Heads coming to him, and contending with him for some space of time, till a Cloud of a blood-red colour overshadowed the whole Appearance.</head>
               <p>Two credible persons, living at <hi>Ford,</hi> a Village in <hi>Netherbury</hi> Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rish in the County of <hi>Dorcet,</hi> rising very early in the morning, <hi>July</hi> 6
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:55733:5"/> 1662, did observe the Sun to look as red as blood, and presently they beheld near the Sun the perfect form or a Man; and after that they saw a multitude of Mens Heads coming from the North, which drew very near to the Man, and seemed very earnestly to contend with him for a good space of time, thrusting him up and down, till at length a great Cloud of a blood-red colour did overshadow the whole Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance. This Information hath been received from the Spectators themselves, who are ready to testifie the truth of it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>VII.</hi> The form of a Steeple seen in the Heavens, with the top downwards.</head>
               <p>About the 7th of <hi>July</hi> 1662, near <hi>Coventry</hi> in the County of <hi>War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wick,</hi> was seen in the Heavens by divers credible persons, the form of a very fair Church with the top and Steeple downward. It appeared a considerable space of time together, and then vanished. This the eye-witnesses themselves do testifie.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>VIII.</hi> Three Moons, fiery Vapours, like Steeples inverted, the forms of Cannon bullets, and the noise of small Guns, seen and heard in the Heavens.</head>
               <p>On the 9th of <hi>July</hi> 1662, at <hi>Limehouse</hi> in the Parish of <hi>Stepney</hi> near <hi>London,</hi> between eleven and twelve of the clock at night, was seen in the Heavens toward the West, three Moons together, with full bodies, and of an exceeding red colour. They stood in a Triangular figure, and were very near to each other. They were all in a continual moving posture, and seemed to contend with each other for some space of time: then they seemed to break in pieces, and immediately sunk into a black Cloud which was underneath, and so disappeared. Then there seemed to come forth a Vapour of Fire, rising out of the same Cloud, and did ascend up into the Sky, in the perfect form and shape of a sharp Steeple, with its great end upward; and when it had remained for a while, it brake into pieces, which fell down several wayes; and then was plainly heard the noise of small Guns about the same Cloud. Assoon as the noise of these Guns ceased, there arose another Vapour of Fire out of the same Cloud, which ascended after the manner and in the form with the other, and then it soon brake to pieces, and the noise of small Guns followed as before. After this, there arose a third Vapour of Fire out of the same Cloud; this much exceeded the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:55733:6"/> other in bigness, and did also rise with greater force; and from it did ascend round Balls, in perfect forms of Cannon bullets; and then the noise of small Guns followed as before, and then all disappeared. The black Cloud also passed away, which all the time before seemed as if it had been fixed in the Air; and there were seen none other Clouds in the Sky but that one Cloud, it being an extraordinary bright and Star-light night. This whole Relation we received immediately from an eye-witness.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>IX.</hi> Two Suns seen together in the Heavens.</head>
               <p>Near <hi>Chard</hi> in the County of <hi>Devon</hi> were seen, on the 12th of <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> 1662, in the morning, by several credible persons, Two Suns in the Heavens together. They were both so exceeding bright, that the false Sun could not easily be discerned from the true one, till the one disappeared, and the other remained. This is also confirmed by Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters from unquestionable hands, who received the certainty of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation from the eye-witnesses.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>X.</hi> The Sun and Moon appearing in a strange manner, several dayes one after another.</head>
               <p>In many places of the Nation for three of four dayes together, <hi>viz. July</hi> the 11th, 12th, 13th, 14th, the Sun and Moon have appeared in a very strange and unusual manner, especially toward the rising and setting: the Sun losing its brightness, and though no Cloud interpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, it might easily be looked upon without the least prejudice or of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence to the eyes. More particularly, it was so on the 13th day, when it cast little or no shadow for a good part of that day, especially in the morning: which in <hi>Lincolnshire, Leicestershire,</hi> and <hi>Essex,</hi> with many other places, was taken notice of by Hundreds of people, to their great astonishment and amazement. And particularly at <hi>Wellen</hi> in <hi>Hertfordshire,</hi> it was very much observed by a person of consider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Quality in that Town; and one employed in his Majesties ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, who with the Minister of the place, and several other the Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants there, did for some good space of time behold it, and have since spoken of it, as a very strange thing, to several in <hi>London.</hi> About <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verly</hi> in <hi>York-shire,</hi> two or three hours before Sun-set, on the 13th day of <hi>July,</hi> it was as red as Blood, or (to use the Country-mens own phrase) like Blood in a Butchers bowl; which was very dreadfull and terrible to the Spectators, who were very many; and from some
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:55733:6"/> of them we received this account. The Moon also the same night, in several places, and more particularly in <hi>Essex,</hi> did appear as red as Blood. This also we received immediately from the Spectators, who were many, and persons of very good quality in the Country.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>XI.</hi> Three Suns seen together in the Firmament.</head>
               <p>Also, upon the same 13th of <hi>July</hi> 1662, about nine of the clock in the morning, near <hi>Oseth</hi> in the County of <hi>Essex,</hi> there appeared for several hours three Suns together in the Firmament. The true Sun was of a very bloody colour, and so continued all that day: the other two Suns were very pale. Of this were many Spectators, from some of whom we received this Information.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>XII.</hi> Several strange fiery Meteors seen in the Heavens, and falling to the Earth, were turned into a blue matter, which being touched, did ascend in smoak.</head>
               <p>At <hi>Sutton,</hi> near <hi>Mansfield,</hi> in the County of <hi>Notingham,</hi> on the 13th of <hi>July</hi> 1662, five or six very honest and credible persons, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing abroad toward Sun-setting, did observe the Sun to look exceeding red, as also the Sky round about it; soon after there appeared many flames of Fire which did encompass the body of the Sun; several sheets of this Fire did with great swiftness fly several wayes, some whereof did come down to the Earth perpendicularly, and did fall upon the Spectators, and on the ground round about them, but they had not the least prejudice by it: then it converted it self into a blue matter, like Indico, or Pouder-blue, and as soon as they touched it, it ascended in smoak. Great satisfaction concerning the truth of this hath been given by the eye-witnesses themselves.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>XIII.</hi> Seven Suns seen together in the Heavens.</head>
               <p>On the same 13th of <hi>July</hi> 1662, at <hi>Stoke-Lane</hi> in the County of <hi>Dorset,</hi> several persons did observe the Sun when it was about half an hour high, to look very red about the edges of it, and very black in the midst; then that part of it which was black turned bright, and the edges of it, which before looked bright, became black, and so
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:55733:7"/> successively two or three times together. Afterwards it turned into se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral strange shapes, which they that beheld them could not express, and the parts seemed to strive each with other. At length there ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared Seven Suns together, which continued for a little time, and then they all joyned in one again, in the midst of which there ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared a dark Cloud, in the form of a black Glove, as the Spectators apprehended; the edges were exceeding bright, from them seemed to fall to the Earth very great streams of Blood. This was first disco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered by a Man and his Wife, and afterwards seen by many other credible persons of the Neighbourhood, who do attest the truth of the whole story as it is here related.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>XIV.</hi> An innumerable company of Flyes, and a Fiery Meteor, seen in the Air.</head>
               <p>On the 14th of <hi>July</hi> 1662, at a Town called <hi>Wootton</hi> in the County of <hi>Bedford,</hi> and about three miles from <hi>Bedford</hi> Town, were seen an innumerable company of Flyes, flying in the Air, and in ther motion making a very great noise, as if many swarms of Bees had been up together. They flew North-east: and at the same time there ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared a fiery Meteor, not far from the Steeple of the said Town, and directly pointing towards it: This continued near half an hour, and then suddenly vanished. This is affirmed as a most certain truth by the eye-witnesses themselves.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>XV:</hi> The appearance of two Armies in the Skie, engaging each other.</head>
               <p>Upon the 15th of <hi>July</hi> 1662, divers persons Inhabitants of <hi>Great Linford</hi> and <hi>Haversham,</hi> near <hi>Newport-Pagnel</hi> in the County of <hi>Bucks,</hi> did (to their amazement) see in the Air very low, a whitish Cloud, and, as it were under this Cloud, the appearance of two Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, which seemed to engage each other, and after a while both disappeared. This is attested by the Spectators themselves, some of which were so affrighted at the fight, that they cryed out, <hi>The World is at an end.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>XVI.</hi> The form of a Man seen in the Heavens, with a long Pike in his hand, pointing towards the Earth.</head>
               <p>At a place called <hi>Layland</hi> about four miles from <hi>Preston</hi> in the County of <hi>Lancaster,</hi> a Gentleman, with divers others of that Town,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:55733:7"/> did, on or near the 16th of <hi>July</hi> 1662, (being a very clear and Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shine day) see in the Heavens the form of a Man drawing forth a long Pike, and pointing with it towards the Earth, and then drawing it up a gain very plainly, and then immediately vanished.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>XVII.</hi> Two Suns seen together in the Firmament.</head>
               <p>About two miles from <hi>Chard</hi> in the County of <hi>Somerset,</hi> on the 19th of <hi>July</hi> 1662, being Saturday, towards the evening, were seen by many credible persons, two Suns together in the Firmament. They were both so bright that they could not discern which was the false Sun, till after it had for a while continued, it disappeared, and the true Sun went on its course.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>XVIII.</hi> The form of a Man, with a Rod in his hand; as also of another on horseback, with a Bonnet on his head: with several Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of Horse and Foot charging each other; seen in the Heavens.</head>
               <p>On the 20th of <hi>July</hi> 1662, about an hour after Sun-set, several persons Inhabitants of <hi>Chillington</hi> near <hi>Chard,</hi> in the County of <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merset,</hi> saw towards the West, a very long Cloud, of an extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry azure colour, and immediately out of the Cloud came forth the form of a Man with a Rod in his hand, and on the top of it there was a thing like a Brush; he held it forward in his hand for a little while, and vanished. And then issued forth of the same Cloud, a Man on horseback, having a Sword in his hand, and one of his arms set by his side: he had also a flat round Bonnet on his head, and something hanging down behind him like a Feather. After which they saw se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Companies of Horse and Foot marching two in a Rank, and then vanishing, and immediately others successively appearing in their rooms; they plainly discerned the Footmen to be armed with Mus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quets, and the Horses to march very stately, touching their breasts with their noses. Two Parties of them, the one from the East and the other from the West, did charge each other with great fierceness, and then all disappeared. This whole Relation is testified by the Spectators themselves.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="section">
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:55733:8"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>XIX.</hi> The appearance of two great Armies, encountring each other, seen in the Heavens.</head>
               <p>Upon Monday the 21th of <hi>July</hi> 1662, at <hi>Burwast</hi> in the County of <hi>Sussex,</hi> was seen, about six of the clock in the morning, by several honest and credible persons, the appearance of a great Army in the Heavens, coming out of the North, about <hi>Brightling,</hi> a Town within a mile or two from <hi>Burwast:</hi> Then they beheld in like manner the appearance of another Army, marching out of the South. They saw these two Armies advance toward each other, till at length they were engaged in fight: The Southern Army was beaten, and totally routed by the Northern. The Spectators themselves do attest the truth of this, and it is generally believed amongst the Inhabitants there.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>XX.</hi> A Fire, and the appearance of two great Persons combating with each other; seen in the Heavens.</head>
               <p>Much about the same time, two Gentlemen, Inhabitants of <hi>Leam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster</hi> in the County of <hi>Hereford,</hi> having occasion to be out late, as they were coming home on horseback, about ten of the clock at night, did plainly see a very dreadful Fire in the Air; and after that they beheld the appearance of two great Persons fighting and combating each with other. These two Gentlemen, the one whereof is a Lawyer, are not under the least suspition of <hi>Phanaticism,</hi> yet do attest the truth of this Story.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>XXI.</hi> A strange Cloud, sending forth great flashes of Fire, seen in the Air; and on the top of it the form of a Man's Head, of a very large proportion.</head>
               <p>Upon the 30th of <hi>July</hi> 1662, three credible persons going from <hi>London</hi> to <hi>Newington-Green,</hi> about eight of the clock at night, saw a great Cloud before them, which hung very low in the Air: It sent forth very many and great flashes of Fire, which were very terrible to behold. At length there appeared on the top of the Cloud, the form of a Man's Head, of a very large proportion: his hair was of a perfect black colour; they saw Fire ascend out of the Cloud, against
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:55733:8"/> the Head, as it had come out of a Musket. One of the Spectators being a Woman, was so extreamly affrighted, that she would not go further in that way wherein they were, but prevailed with the rest to turn into another path which led to Sir <hi>George Whitmoor's</hi> house, and so are able to give no further account; but they do all constantly affirm the truth of what hath been here related.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>XXII.</hi> The form of a great Tree seen in the Heavens.</head>
               <p>On the same 30th of <hi>July,</hi> 1662. at <hi>Chillington</hi> in <hi>Sussex,</hi> near <hi>Lewis,</hi> several discreet and credible Persons, about eight or nine of the Clock in the Evening, did see in the Heavens towards the North, the form of a goodly Tree resembling an Oak, which was suddenly all in a flame, but it immediately extinguished, and the Tree ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared again in its former shape, only the top of it seemed to be sunk somewhat flat; then one half of the Tree turned very pale, but the other part retained still its former colour, and presently the whole Tree was all in a flame again, twice together, a very little time interveening; but, the flame soon vanishing, the Tree appeared a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain to the spectators as it was at the first: Then they saw over the top of the Tree the resemblance of two Horns, the one pointing to the East, and the other to the West; and in a very short time that which was toward the West vanished, and presently the whole Tree was in a flame again; but there arose a great brush of weather on the West-side of the Tree, and the night coming on, the spectators were forced to return into their houses, and can give no further ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count than what is here inserted, which according to the report of some amongst them, is true to a circumstance.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>XXIII.</hi> A Fiery Meteor in the form of an Ensign, or Banner, seen in the Heavens.</head>
               <p>Upon the 31 of <hi>July,</hi> 1662. about six of the Clock in the Evening, there appeared in the Heavens near <hi>Dover,</hi> on the Southerly-side of the Town, a fiery Meteor in the form of an Ensign, or Banner, broad at one end, and narrow at the other, about fourteen yards in leng<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h (so near as the Spectators were able to judge) it was of a fiery red colour: It flew with great swiftness from about the Sea-mark, called, the <hi>Devil's-drop,</hi> toward <hi>Dover Castle,</hi> and so over the Castle about a
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:55733:9"/> mile in length, winding in its motion like a Roman S, and then gradually vanished. This is attested by the Spectators themselves.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>XXIV.</hi> Two Suns seen together in the Heavens.</head>
               <p>Near a Town called <hi>Froom,</hi> in the County of <hi>Dorset,</hi> on the 5th of <hi>August</hi> 1662, early in the morning, several very credible Persons did see two Suns together in the Firmament, the one was somewhat bigger than the other, and they were at a good distance from each other; after they had a while beheld them, a Cloud over-shadowed the false Sun, and it appeared no more. This the Spectators them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves do testifie.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>XXV.</hi> An Army of Horsemen seen in the Heavens.</head>
               <p>On the first of <hi>September</hi> 1662, at <hi>Steeple-Ashen</hi> in <hi>Wiltshire,</hi> about five miles from the <hi>Devizes,</hi> there was seen in the Air, by divers cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible Persons, a great Body of Horse, which stood upon a Cloud as red as blood, the Riders had their Swords drawn in their hands; they continued a good space of time, to the grear terror and amazement of the Spectators, and then vanished.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>XXVI.</hi> A great Body of Footmen seen in the Heavens.</head>
               <p>Also on the same first of <hi>September,</hi> within a mile of the <hi>Devizes,</hi> there were seen in the Heavens a great Body of Footmen, armed with Pikes and other Weapons, and a man on Horse-back seemed to march in the Front of them; they continued a while in the view of the Spectators, and then vanished.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>XXVII.</hi> A great Shoal of Fishes, and a Dragon, together with a Wood, and two Armies seen in the Heavens.</head>
               <p>Upon the 13th of <hi>September</hi> 1662, some Passengers coming by Water, in the evening, from <hi>Chelsy</hi> to <hi>London,</hi> did, not far from <hi>Fox-Hall,</hi> see in the Heavens, the appearance of a great Shoal of Fishes, and one of a very large size in the Head of them, and another of the same proportion in the middle; then in another quarter of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:55733:9"/> they saw the form of a great Dragon, and out of his mouth did issue abundance of Smoak and Fire also, and in the Smoak were several strange forms, which the Spectators are not willing to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover. After that, they saw the appearance of a great Wood, and on one side of it some scattered Horsemen, who drew up together till they became a considerable Body; and in the Head of them ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared a man on Horse-back, with something extraordinary on his head. And near another part of the Wood they also discovered some few scattered Parties of an Army, who also, as the former, did draw together into a Body. Then they saw the Wood set on fire and burn till it was consumed; and being much affrighted at the sight, they ran their Boat on shore, and can give no further account. But they confidently affirm the truth of what hath been here related, and do daily offer to testifie it upon Oath, which many sober and discreet Persons, in and about this City, who have had it from their own mouths, have often declared.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>XXVIII.</hi> The Form of two Armies engaging each other, seen in the Heavens.</head>
               <p>On the 3d of <hi>October</hi> 1662, within a mile of <hi>Upingham</hi> in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Rutland,</hi> were seen in the Heavens; first, the several forms of a Lion and a Unicorn: then appeared the form of two compleat Armies; the one marching out of the East, or South-east, and the other out of the North, who did very fiercely encounter each other; and after a very hot dispute on both sides, many did seem to lye dead upon the place, and some with their heads off. This is attested by some of the Spectators themselves.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:55733:10"/>
            <head>Several PRODIGIES, and Monstrous Births, seen on the Earth; together with some dreadful Whirle-winds and violent Storms: All which, except some very few, have happened within the month of <hi>July,</hi> 1662.</head>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>I.</hi> Drops of Blood often seen on the top of the Milk in the Milk-Pans.</head>
               <p>FOr about ten or eleven Months together, the year past, one Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>striss <hi>Duncomb,</hi> who is Tennant to Esquire <hi>Cheyney</hi> at <hi>Drayton</hi> in the County of <hi>Bucks,</hi> did every morning find several drops of Blood upon the top of her Milk-pans, so that she was constrained to dip upon the Cream with a linnen cloth and take off the Blood: She kept all her Milk-bowls covered, and caused some to watch several nights, who found that as the Cream did rise, so the Blood did rise with it in little spots, and yet the Pans were skimmed in due time, according to their usual custome, then it was like fresh Blood issuing out of a wound; but if it stood longer than ordinary (which they often made an experiment of) then those drops turned blue like blood that hath been long out of the body, and is ready to putrifie. This In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation comes from one nearly related to the said <hi>Duncomb,</hi> who was well acquainted with the certainty of it, and did affirm it in the presence of near forty credible Persons at one time, from some of whom we received the foregoing account.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>II.</hi> A Wind-mill all in a flame, and not burnt.</head>
               <p>Upon the 5th or 6th of <hi>July</hi> 1662, several Persons being in a Field near <hi>Nottingham,</hi> in Thundring weather, did see a Wind-mill at some distance from them all in a flame, insomuch that the Specta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors thought it had been burnt and consumed; but when they came near to it, they found that it was not in the least prejudiced by the fire, only one Rake-head was burnt in the Mill. This is testified by eye witnesses, who are Persons of credit and reputation.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:55733:10"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>III.</hi> A Mushroom growing up in a night to an incredible bigness.</head>
               <p>Also, much about the time last mentioned, in a Garden in the Town of <hi>Nottingham,</hi> there grew up in one night a Mushroom, which was at least four very large spans in compass; the form of it was like a Pillow on which Bonelace is wont to be made. This is at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tested by some who were eye witnesses, and measured it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>IV.</hi> A Woman delivered of Four compleat Children, and Three false Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions, within the space of three quarters of a year.</head>
               <p>By Letters from very good hands in the City of <hi>Coventry,</hi> we are certainly informed, that the Wife of one <hi>Heycock</hi> an Inhabitant of that City, and a Souldier under Sir <hi>Arthur Cayley</hi> in the County Troop, was, presently after <hi>Michaelmass,</hi> in the year 1661, delivered at her full time of two Female Children, who were likely to live, but in few dayes after they died. The same Woman, a fortnight after <hi>Midsommer,</hi> which was about the 10th day of <hi>July</hi> ensuing, was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered of two Boyes, very large and lusty Children, but died the same day they were born: the Woman still continuing very ill, was delivered about a day or two after, of three false Conceptions with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out form; the one of which was as big as either of the two Boyes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore mentioned; the other two were somewhat less. So that this Woman brought forth in three quarters of a years time, four perfect Childeren alive born, and at full growth; and three false Concepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons besides. This is a thing notoriously known, and publickly spo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of in that City.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>V.</hi> Great drops of Blood seen upon the Leaves of several Trees in an Orchard.</head>
               <p>About the 21 of <hi>July</hi> 1662, several Persons, inhabitants of <hi>Ashby,</hi> in the County of <hi>Leicester,</hi> did behold the Sun in the Afternoon, for some hours together, to be as red as blood, and all that time it did reflect no beams or heat to the Earth. At the same time a Servant to a Minister in that Town went into his Orchard, and came suddenly in again, affirming that all the Trees in the Orchard were full of ripe
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:55733:11"/> Cherries; whereupon the Minister himself went into the Orchard, and found upon the Leaves of most of his Trees great drops of blood, very thick and round, as if they had been ripe Cherries upon the Trees. This the Minister himself, a man of good credit and reputation, testifies the truth of.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>VI.</hi> A great and strange Fish cast up upon the shore, near <hi>Preston</hi> in Lancashire.</head>
               <p>Upon the 24th of <hi>July</hi> 1662, at <hi>Litham</hi> (a place belonging to one Mr. <hi>Thomas Clifton</hi>) about two miles f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>om <hi>Preston,</hi> in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Lancaster,</hi> a very strange Fish was cast upon the shoar; It was about four yards in length, and as big as an ordinary Horse, the fore-feet were as long as a man's Arm; the hinder-feet much shorter, but broad like unto Fishes Finns: it roared most dreadfully like a Bear; On the 30th of <hi>July</hi> it continued alive, since which time we have received no further account concerning it. Multitudes of People came to see it, and no doubt is made of the truth of the whole Relation, which comes from some of the eye-witnesses them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>VII.</hi> A Serpent of a great and unusual proportion seen by divers Persons.</head>
               <p>Also, much about the same time, and nine miles from the place mentioned in the fore-going particular, many very credible Persons have often seen a most dreadful Serpent, which frequently coms forth out of a Wood that belongs to one Mr. <hi>Walmly</hi> of <hi>Dunkin-Hall.</hi> The Spectators have computed the length of it to be about five or six yards, and did judge it to be thicker than the biggest Cart Axle-tree. It is so great, that some, who have viewed the place where it some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times lay near a Well in one Dr. <hi>Rushton's</hi> Ground, do affirm, that it made such an impression upon the ground as if an Ox, or some more large and pondrous Beast had lain there. This whole Relation is reported, and testified by several Persons of credit in the County, who have been Spectators of this terrible and prodigious Creature, the like whereof hath been seldom or very rarely seen or heard of in this Island.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>VIII.</hi> A great Whirlwind near Dover, in the County of Kent.</head>
               <p>On the 25th of <hi>July</hi> 1662, and about three of the clock in the afternoon, there happened a very strange Whirlwind in the <hi>Mason-Du-Field,</hi>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:55733:11"/> between the Castle and Town of <hi>Dover,</hi> at the upper end of which Field the Wind took up divers Sheaves or Wads of Pease an incredible hight into the Air, and then carried them out of the said Field, and over the Town, and so into the Sea, that it is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved they were carried two or three miles before they fell into the Sea. It also took up some Calves, and other small Cattel, and threw them into a ditch. A Hoy likewise in the Road was almost over-set by it. This Relation comes immediately from the eye-witnesses, and is most certainly true.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>IX.</hi> A Woman delivered of a very strange Monster.</head>
               <p>Upon the same 25th of <hi>July</hi> 1662, one <hi>Ann Walton</hi> of <hi>Poplar,</hi> near <hi>Black-wall,</hi> in the Parish of <hi>Stepney</hi> and County of <hi>Middlesex,</hi> was delivered of a strange and monstrous Birth: It seemed to have neither Face nor Head, but a great black Lump reached down to the Breast, much larger and bigger than the ordinary proportion of a Childs Head: In the lower-part, and the sides of it, it was loose, and being lifted up, underneath it the Face of the Child appeared in all parts well proportioned, only the Ears were drawn down to the middle of the Neather Jaw-bone, and the Forehead lower than or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary. The out-side of the Flap, which so lay over the Face of the Child, as is before described, was of a black colour, and the hinder-part of it covered with small downy hairs: the in-side of it was white, and hollow like a Shield, and was fastened to the Forehead and sides of the Face; it was lined with a thin bone, not much thick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er than a strong lanthorn horn, which an Artist, who was present, did suppose to be the Skull of the Child; when this Shield or Hood was turned from off the Face backward, it seemed to be like the brim of a Hat, or a Child's Bonnet turned up before, The Feet of the Child were deformed, and irregular, for both of them turned to the right-side: Also one of its Eyes was much bigger than the other. This Monster was exposed to sight for many dayes together, and multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes of People, from several parts of the City, did view it, and amongst them some Chirurgions of Note; one of which doth attest the truth of the fore-going description of it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="section">
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:55733:12"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>X.</hi> A Paving Stone in a Cathedral, did of it self rise out of its place a quarter of a yard high, and fell almost into its place again.</head>
               <p>By Letters from extraordinary good hands out of <hi>Ireland,</hi> we are assured that about the 28th of <hi>July</hi> 1662, in the Cathedral at the City of <hi>Limbrick</hi> in that Kingdom, a Paving Stone about twelve inches long, and eight inches broad, did of it self arise at least a quarter of a yard high from the ground, and turned it self round, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in a very little, fell directly into its place again. This is attested amongst others, by a zealous Son and Daughter of the Church, who were eye-witnesses.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>XI.</hi> The great Storm of Hail, in several parts of the Nation.</head>
               <p>That most strange and dreadful Storm of Hail, which happened on the 30th of <hi>July</hi> 1662, hath been generally known, and taken no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of throughout the whole Nation, especially in the North-west part of it: And because of the great variety of most remarkable Circumstances which did attend it in the several places where it hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened, we shall give a faithful account of the Extracts of divers Letters from the most authentick hands, who inhabited where the the Storm fell, and were sad Spectators of the dismal Effects of it. That which we shall begin with, is, what we have received from Persons of unquestionable Reputation, living at or near <hi>Drayton</hi> in <hi>Shropshire,</hi> (the Town which his Majesty hath so much kindness for, because it was casually burnt as he went thorow it to the fatal Fight at <hi>Worcester</hi>) the substance of what they say, is as followeth.</p>
               <p>That on Wednesday, the 30th of <hi>July</hi> 1662, such a Storm of Hail fell within half a mile of <hi>Drayton,</hi> and thereabouts, as hath spoiled a great part of their Corn, by beating it out of the Ears, as if they had been threshed on a Floor. Most of the Hailstones were at the least six inches about; and one was taken up which was half a yard long; several Partridges and Geese, with other Fowls, and some Sheep also were killed by them.</p>
               <p>Another writes, that near <hi>Drayton,</hi> the Hailstones lay half a yard thick upon the ground, and that most of their Corn in the Field was utterly spoiled, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:55733:12"/>
               <p>A Third sayes, that on the 30th of <hi>July</hi> 1662, about one of the clock in the afternoon, this Hail storm began first about a place cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Stoak-heath,</hi> which is two miles on the South-side of <hi>Drayton,</hi> it fell about a mile in breadth, and three miles in length; several Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, who measured the stones, found them to be six inches about; It destroyed and cut in pieces most of the Corn growing in divers Fields, especially in those belonging to the Towns called <hi>Lonklow, Sutton, Drayton,</hi> and <hi>Spoonly;</hi> one man (as is supposed) hath lost two hundred pounds worth of Corn by this storm. Divers did that day buy meat at <hi>Drayton</hi> for their Reape<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, who were to Reap their Corn the next day, but when they came home they had none to reap.</p>
               <p>By Letters also, together with verbal Information from consider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Persons ey-witnesses in the County of <hi>Warwick,</hi> we are assured that in several places in that County the people were very sensible of this dreadful Storm. At <hi>Fletchamsteed,</hi> about two miles from <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventry,</hi> the Hailstones were very great, and some of them of very strange shapes like Crowns, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>At <hi>Alcester</hi> the Stones also were very large, and of divers forms, and extream hard, like congealed Ice, they tasted very Salt like <hi>Salsa Prunella;</hi> some of them have been kept to this day, and are not at all wasted.</p>
               <p>The like also was at <hi>Sugborrow</hi> in the same County.</p>
               <p>Also, at <hi>Oswestry</hi> in <hi>Shropshire,</hi> the Storm did beat down the Corn as it stood on the ground all to pieces; it also killed abundance of Fowl, and Sheep, and Lambs. Three men that could not get shel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, were so battered, that they could neither go nor stand; the Hailstones which fell, were judged to be near as big as Hen-eggs.</p>
               <p>A Person of credit, living in or near <hi>Northampton,</hi> writes that the Storm of Hail fell in those parts also, and that the stones were bigger than Pidgeons eggs.</p>
               <p>From <hi>Eardly</hi> in <hi>Stafford-shire,</hi> a very credible Person writes thus; That on Wednesday, <hi>July</hi> 30 1662, between two and three of the clock in the afternoon, there happened a great Storm of Thunder which made such a continual strange noise in the Air, that it struck a terror into all that heard it, there was no intermission for a long time. Also there fell a showre of Hailstones as big as Hen-eggs, some were five, some six, and some seven inches about. I my self measured one after the Storm was over, and a good part of it melted, yet then it was five inches about. Here was a Gentleman who measured some of them by a good big Watch, and they were full as big as it. With<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:55733:13"/> half a mile of us the Hailstones lay upon the ground a quarter of a yard thick. Here was a Neighbors man getting in a Load of Hay, and his Horses (as all others) would not be ruled, but ran about as mad, which forced the Man to be in the Storm, and his back, shoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and arms were black and blue with the stones falling upon him. It hath done much hurt to Barly, and struck it out of the Ear as though it had been threshed. We were all in these parts much affraid and amazed. The stones had several shapes; the least of them were as big as Tennis Balls, and many as big as Duck-eggs, which with the continual strange noise in the Air was very terrible to us.</p>
               <p>At a Town called <hi>Ormeschurch,</hi> about twelve miles from <hi>Liver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pool</hi> in <hi>Lancashire,</hi> the effects of this Storm were very sad; an account whereof take in a Letter written by a Person of credit and quality, an Inhabitant in that Town, to an eminent Citizen of <hi>London,</hi> which was <hi>verbatim</hi> as followeth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>There hath been such a Hail-storm in this Town, as I suppose no man now living ever saw before. It happened on Wednesday last at three of the clock. It beat down all our Apples, spoiled our Corn, broke all our Glass Windows on that side of the houses where the Wind sate. It cut the Lead in pieces. It was so violent that it split the Apples as if they had been bruised between two stones. Many affirm they took up Hailstones which were eight inches about. But I dare affirm that many fell as big as Pullets-eggs. All the French Wheat in</hi> Seston, Aughton, <hi>and</hi> Ormeschurch <hi>parish ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly spoiled; I have three Acres which I never intend to shear. Our Barly and Wheat much damaged, I do not hear that it hath done much hurt, but in these three Parishes,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>By Letters also out of <hi>Cheshire</hi> we do understand that the People in those parts felt the sad effects of this Storm.</p>
               <p>A credible Person from <hi>Chester</hi> writes, That a tempestuous Storm of Hail happened in the afternoon, on the 30th of <hi>July</hi> 1662, the Hailstones were of an extraordinary magnitude, and weighed a quarter of a pound; others were six and eight inches compass. A man coming over the Forrest of <hi>Dalamore,</hi> saw a piece of congealed Ice, as he conceived, which was as big as an ordinary Child; much Corn was also broken and spoyled, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Another writes, That at <hi>Maxfield</hi> the Hailstones were as big as Goose-eggs, and that they did so break up the Pavement in the streets there, that the People could not conveniently pass along through them.</p>
               <p>Another, an Inhabitant of the said Town of <hi>Maxfield,</hi> affirms that some of the Hailstones were broad ones like the bottom of a Venice
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:55733:13"/> glass, with pearls in the middle, and some had pearls round about. The form of them were strange, some like faces, some like hands with fingers, and some like sword-hilts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A Fourth confirms the substance of what the others have related, and withal adds this Circumstance, That the Storm happened on the same day that the Biship came to <hi>Chester</hi> to receive the Subscriptions of the Clergy to the New Liturgy; a considerable number of them, to the astonishment of the Bishop, did accordingly subscribe, though they never saw nor read the Book in their lives. And doubtless these Loyal Subjects, and most Dutiful and Obedient Sons, when his Lordship shall receive his Commission to require it, will give the same honour to the Mass-Book, and after that, if need be, to the Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kish Alcharon it self, believing it to be a mortal sin to dispute the Orders and Commands of their Superiours.</p>
               <p>We shall close up what we have to say about this particular Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, with the Account we received from <hi>Buckingham,</hi> and the parts adjacent. One writes, that as he was Riding near a place called <hi>Fenmore,</hi> about three miles from <hi>Buckingham,</hi> between one and two of the clock in the afternoon, on the 30th of <hi>July</hi> 1662, there fell a very dreadful Storm of Hail, the stones were about the bigness of Carbine-bullets, hard and clear; when he came a mile nearer to <hi>Buckingham,</hi> and as he passed thorow <hi>Tingewyck,</hi> they fell as big as Musket-bullets, or Damsons. Within less than half a mile of <hi>Buck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingham</hi> Town, he went into a field, and there saw the Ashes of a shock of Wheat which had been burnt by a flash of Fire which did accompany this Hail-storm; and there also he saw a Woman, who was struck down with the said flash of Fire, laid upon a Beir, and carried into <hi>Buckingham</hi> Town, where the Hailstones fell as big as Walnuts, and were very hard and clear, like those which he saw be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in other places.</p>
               <p>Another known credible Person, dwelling at <hi>Buckingham,</hi> informs us, that the same day and time, there appeared in the Sky a very black Cloud, in form like a Wool-pack; the North-side of it was exceeding black, and the South-side very fiery, and suddenly there followed a great and terrible storm of Thunder and Lightening, and most hideous ratlings in the Air, and immediately the storm of Hail fell; the stones were four, five, and six inches about, full as big as Walnuts, or little Hen-eggs; some of them were forked like the head of a forked Arrow. At the same time also a shock of Corn in <hi>Buckingham</hi> field was consumed with Fire from Heaven; and one <hi>Penelope Macham</hi> scorched to death by it; And another, a Widow
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:55733:14"/> Woman, taken up for dead, who, it is feared, will hardly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover.</p>
               <p>And here let one Circumstance be taken notice of by the Reader, that the day of this Storm at <hi>Buckingham,</hi> was the day of the Bishop of <hi>Lincoln</hi>'s Visitation at <hi>Stony-Stratford</hi> in that County; where also a very great Storm of dreadful Execrations and Excommunications fell from his Lordship upon the <hi>Old</hi> non-conforming <hi>Presbyterians</hi> in his Diocess, which we are confident they will better escape than his Lordship, and the rest of his Levitical Fraternity can. The storm of God's Vengeance, now impending them, whereof many wise and good men do believe that this was a most plain and significant warn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>XII.</hi> The strange Whirl-wind in Cheshire.</head>
               <p>On the same 30th of <hi>July</hi> 1662, in the afternoon, there happened near <hi>Maxfield</hi> in <hi>Cheshire,</hi> a very strange and dreadful Whirl-wind, a true and exact account whereof from several Persons of great Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity and Discretion, take as followeth.</p>
               <p>Upon a place called <hi>Bosly Moor,</hi> about a mile and an half from <hi>Maxfield,</hi> there arose a Cloud, like to a great Pillar of Smoak, which seemed to have fire in it; in height it was like a Church-steeple, the breadth about 15 or 20 yards, which making a most dreadful noise, went but slowly, near the ground, for about six or seven miles, level<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling all before it. It threw down all the Fences, which in those parts are generally Stone-walls; many of the Stones were carried a very great distance from the places where they first were. Passing over a Corn-field, it laid it as even with the ground as if it had been trod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den down with the Feet. It also took away with it a parcel of Hay which stood on Cocks in a Field, judged to be about five or six Load, all which, except about the quantity of a load and an half, was swept clean away, and not an handful of it to be found either in that Field or any where else, only it left behind it, in that field, a great Tree which it had brought with it from some other place. It also took up great Logs of old Timber, which had layen so long upon the ground that they were almost sunk into it, and removed them three or four Rods at the least. It tore a Barn of five Bayes, and shattered it to pieces, the beams of it were carried above a quarter of a mile; all the Gates and Gate-posts which were within its reach were carried away by it. It took up a Cart, and carried it at least half a mile. A Stone-house, which was laid in Lime and Morter, was beaten to
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:55733:14"/> pieces by it. It passed through a Wood belonging to one Mr. <hi>Joderly</hi> of <hi>Yeardly,</hi> which was very full of great Timber Trees, but it tore down all before it, and turned over about an hundred Timber Trees, some of which were about three fathom thick, and laid the roots up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, so that it made a kind of a Glade or Riding thorow that Wood. It pleased the Lord that this Storm happening in Moorish ground, which was not Inhabited, did the less hurt either to Man or Beast: We cannot learn that any Cattel were killed, only extreamly affright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and in several places they ran bellowing up and down, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived no hurt. The People also were extreamly terrified, and cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out, that the Last day was come. One man who was Mowing in a Field, had his Sith taken from him, and he falling flat down, and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king hold of the long Grass to save himself, was turned over several times, but not hurt. A little Shop also belonging to a poor Woman, was taken up by this Whirl-wind from the ground, and clapt together, and she and her three Children were struck by it also, but they are yet alive, and in hopes of recovery. It continued in its motion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the space of three hours, till it came to a place called <hi>Weely-Bridge,</hi> about six miles from the place where it first arose, and from thence it went up the Hill into <hi>Darbyshire,</hi> and nothing more heard of it. This Relation is the substance of many Letters from Persons of the best repute in those parts, some of whom were eye and ear-witnesses of what is here set down; and the rest also received their Information from such as they could give credit to, who were the Spectators of this great and astonishing Work of the Lord. The truth of it is past all dispute in those parts where it happened.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>XIII.</hi> The strange <hi>Autumn</hi> which we have had this present year, <hi>1662.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>We suppose that the whole Nation hath taken notice of the strange and unusual Autumnal Season which we have had this year. Roses, and several other Flowers; have been as fragrant, and almost as plentiful in the Months of <hi>September</hi> and <hi>October,</hi> as in the Months of <hi>May</hi> and <hi>June.</hi> There hath likewise been great plenty of Straw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berries, Rasberries, and other Fruits which have been frequently sold in <hi>Cheap-side,</hi> and other Markets within the City. Multitudes of Fruit-trees have blossomed again, and brought forth Fruit: some green Apples have been seen by some of us, which we have measured, and they are above two inches about. Some Cherry-trees have also blossomed, and brought forth ripe Cherries again; and it is certainly
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:55733:15"/> true, that a Gardner near <hi>Isleworth</hi> in the County of <hi>Middlesex,</hi> did about the beginning of <hi>October,</hi> gather a ripe Cherry from a May-Cherry-tree. All these particulars are so publickly and commonly known, that there needs nothing be said to induce the Reader to the belief of the truth of any of them. One thing more must not be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, which is as observable as any of the rest, <hi>viz.</hi> On the 18th of <hi>November</hi> 1662, some Gentlemen travelling between <hi>Winsor</hi> and <hi>London,</hi> saw in the Hedges Hawthorn blown as if it had been the beginning of <hi>May;</hi> they brought some of it with them to <hi>London,</hi> which is kept in a Pot of Water, and to be seen at this day.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>XIV.</hi> A Swarm of Bees on the <hi>15th</hi> of October, <hi>1662.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Upon the 15th of <hi>October</hi> 1662, one <hi>John Crips</hi> of <hi>Broughton</hi> in the County of <hi>Bucks,</hi> had a Swarm of Bees which rose from a Hive in his Garden, and settled upon a Tree in or near the Orchard of one Mr. <hi>Duncumb,</hi> adjoyning to the house of the said <hi>Crips.</hi> This is at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tested by several Persons of the said Town, who were eye-witnesses of it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>XV.</hi> The Form of an Army seen upon a March, not far from Kilkenny in Ireland.</head>
               <p>About the same Month of <hi>October</hi> 1662, near <hi>Balline,</hi> seven miles distant from <hi>Kilkenny</hi> in <hi>Ireland,</hi> a Cow-herd keeping his Cattel, saw in an afternoon, the Appearance of a formal Army, consisting (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Computation) of about Six thousand men, marching from the North-ward; whereat being much affrighted, he presently a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wakened some other Cow-herds, who lay sleeping in the field, and they all saw the Army marching in an exact order, <hi>viz.</hi> A Body of Horse in the Van, led by a gallant proper man; after them a Body of Foot, with a Train consisting of several Waggons (whereof one was red) in the middest; and another Body of Horse in the Reer. Whereupon they presently ran to the Town before-mentioned, and gave notice of it to several of the Inhabitants; many of them came forth presently, and saw the same thing. The Army continued in their view for about an hour, at which time the Tall man, who seemed to Lead them, with two or three men more, did march into the Rear, and immediately the whole disappeared. This is attested by several Persons, who were Spectators, and do offer to confirm the truth of it upon their Oaths.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="section">
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:55733:15"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>XVI.</hi> A great Body of Fire falling to the Earth, by which some Barns were set on fire, and much Corn burnt.</head>
               <p>By Letters from credible Persons, we are informed that on the 3d of <hi>November</hi> 1662, near <hi>Warminster</hi> in the County of <hi>Wilts,</hi> there fell down from the Heavens a great Body of Fire about the bigness of a Bushel; it lighted the Country three or four miles compass, and when it came near the Earth, it burst in sunder, and fell like burning Coals in several places, and by it some Barns were set on fire, and much Corn burnt, to the value of many hundreds of pounds. Of this there were many Persons eye-witnesses, who do testifie the truth of the whole Relation.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>XVII.</hi> Young Rookes taken out of a Nest, <hi>November 6, 1662.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Some Gentlemen, living not far from <hi>Stratford</hi> upon <hi>Avon,</hi> in the County of <hi>Warwick,</hi> hearing that there were young Rooks newly hatched in a Rookery at a Town called <hi>Grafton,</hi> about three miles distant from the said <hi>Stratford,</hi> did upon the 6th of <hi>November</hi> 1662, for their further satisfaction in that particular, ride over to the place where they found several Nests with young ones in them; and one which was fledger than the rest they brought away with them, and it is (as we are certainly informed) alive at this day. Two of the aforesaid Gentlemen have assured us of the truth hereof, and we doubt not but upon enquiry any one may be fully satisfied concerning it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>XVIII.</hi> A dreadful Tempest wherein it rained great Drops of Blood.</head>
               <p>By very credible Persons we are informed, that on the 8th of <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vember</hi> 1662, there happened at <hi>Stafford</hi> a very dreadful Tempest, or Whirl-wind, which blew down a part of the Hall there, and did o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther very consideable prejudice besides to several Persons in that Town; and in this Tempest it rained great drops of Blood, which appeared on the Lentels and Door-posts of several of their houses. This, upon enquiry, will be found to be most certainly true.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="section">
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:55733:16"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>XIX.</hi> A great Whirl-wind, accompanied with great Flashes of Fire.</head>
               <p>On the 11th of <hi>November</hi> 1662, there happened at <hi>Derby</hi> a most dreadful Whirl-wind, very like to that which was at <hi>Stafford</hi> two or three dayes before. The Town of <hi>Derby</hi> in four minuts time (for it continued no longer) was damnified more than five hundred Pounds. It blew the Tiles from off the houses, it threw down seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Barns, many Apple-trees, and other Fruit-trees also were torn up by the roots; it turned over great Stone-walls, and broke some Gates in pieces, which were made fast with great Iron bars. All this prejudice was done only in some part of the Town; for from <hi>Alhallows Church</hi> to the <hi>Mary-bridge</hi> there was not ten shillings worth of hurt done; but about the Church and Market-place, and particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly in the <hi>Friar-gate,</hi> the Inhabitants, especially one Mr. <hi>John Dal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> and the <hi>Mayor</hi> of the Town, sustained very great loss. This strange Wind was accompanied with great flashes of Fire, which were very terrible, and seen by the Generality of the Inhabitants; and some do affirm that it rained Blood also. The whole Relation hath been testified by Persons of very good credit and esteem, who were eye-witnesses.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Some strange and Remarkable PRODIGIES which have happened in the WATERS, from the Month of <hi>July,</hi> to the Month of <hi>October,</hi> 1662.</head>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>I.</hi> A great number of Porpusses seen in a River which they were not wont formerly to frequent.</head>
               <p>IT is certified from very good hands, that on the 5th of <hi>July</hi> 1662, in a River near <hi>Newport</hi> in <hi>Wales,</hi> were seen above an hundred Porpusses together, in which River it was rare formerly to see one of that sort of Fishes; And the Inhabitants there do look upon their coming in, in so great numbers, as very strange and prodigious.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:55733:16"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>II.</hi> Divers great Spouts seen in Dover-Road.</head>
               <p>On the 4th of <hi>August</hi> 1662, several very great Spouts were seen in <hi>Dover Road</hi> about quarter Seas over. Some, who first saw them, do testifie that there were seven of them, and that they were about half a mile at least assunder. They did run about half an hour, and ceased, one after another: three of them continued running longer than the rest, so that many Persons who came to the Sea-side late, saw only those three which were indeed much larger than any of the other four. They were big at both ends, and slender in the middle-part of them. Some ancient and experienced Seamen, who were the Specta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, do affirm, that they were bigger than those which are usually seen in the Straits. The People there are much astonished at this prodigious sight, none being now alive that ever saw the like in those Seas.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>III.</hi> A very strange Tide at Dartmouth.</head>
               <p>By Letters from very good hands from <hi>Dartmouth,</hi> we are certified as followeth; That the next day after the Commissioners had new Modelled the Corporation, and turned out the Mayor and several of his Brethren, with other Officers, there happened a very strange Ebbing and Flowing of the Sea in that Harbour, to the astonishment and admiration of all the Spectators, such indeed as was never known or heard of in that place before; for the Harbour sometimes would be quite empty of Water, and then it would Flow in again in so great abundance, and with so much force and violence, that the Ships could hardly ride fast to their Anchors. This was so remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, and so much differing from all other Tides before, that few within the Corporation but took great notice of it, and made their observations upon it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>IV.</hi> Great store of Mackaril taken in the Month of October, <hi>1662.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>It hath been very much observed by many judicious and knowing Persons in the City of <hi>London,</hi> that great and unusual quantities of Mackaril have been taken in this present Month of <hi>October</hi> 1662, they were so plentiful, that they have been sold in <hi>Cheapside</hi>-Market
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:55733:17"/> at reasonable rates; a thing which hath rarely happened heretofore, but upon some signal Changes and Revolutions.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>V.</hi> The Water in a great Lough, or Pond in Ireland, of a bloody colour.</head>
               <p>By Letters from very good hands in <hi>Ireland,</hi> as also by verbal In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation from some Persons of great quality, who lately came out of that Nation, we are assured that on the 4th of <hi>October</hi> 1662, near a Town called <hi>Loughgall,</hi> three miles from <hi>Ardmah,</hi> and two miles from <hi>Charla-mount,</hi> a Lough, or great Lake or Pond of Water, was turned into a blood-red colour, and continued so for several dayes together; during which time it sent forth a most noysome stink, and killed very many of the Fish that were in it. The Wells which were supplied with Water from this Lake were so putrified, that the Inhabitants were forced to cleanse them before they could have any Water for their necessary uses. Several Persons, who went to see it, did fill divers Bottles with the Water, which, as we are from very good hands informed, retains its Bloody Colour to this day. This Prodigy hath greatly alarm'd the Inhabitants in those parts, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard that it is yet so fresh in the memories of many of them, that the same thing happened above twenty years ago, a little before that hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid Rebellion of the Popish-Irish broke forth, wherein so many hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred thousand English Protestants were most barbarously and inhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manely murdered. The People there being very sensible that those bloody miscreants are now upon their return in a fair way towards a settling themselves in such a condition, as may in a great measure capacitate them for a further prosecution of that horrid Murtherous and Rebellious Design (which so many years since they began in that Kingdom, but by the wonderful hand of the Lord, accompany<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and assisting the Forces sent over thither by the Parliament, were at last totally subdued and vanquished) many therefore of the most sober and fore-seeing People there have taken a Course for a speedy Transplantation of themselves and their Families into <hi>England,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving that by this remarkable Prodigie they are warned of God to prepare an Ark for the preservation of them and theirs out of the hands of those blood-thirsty Rebels, whose tender Mercies upon woful and sad experience, they have found to be Cruelties.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:55733:17"/>
            <head>Some strange and remarkable Accidents befalling divers Persons, together with many Eminent and Signal Judgments that have been inflicted upon several Ministers, who have been drawn to do some things in the Worship of God against their Light and Conscience: As also upon others who were of an Imposing and Persecuting Spirit about meer Humane Forms, and Superstitious Ridiculous Ceremonies. From the Month of <hi>February</hi> 1661, to the Month of <hi>November</hi> 1662.</head>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>I.</hi> Some New-Conformists taken away suddenly by death.</head>
               <p>SEveral Ministers, to the number of six or seven, who lived not far from <hi>Chichester,</hi> in the County of <hi>Sussex,</hi> renouncing their former Ordination, and entring into Episcopal Orders; and in other particulars also, shewing their sudden zeal for Conformity, were in a very short time after taken away by death, to the astonishment of the Inhabitants there, who took great notice of the hand of the Lord in that passage of his Providence.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>II.</hi> Five New-Conforming young Ministers, who lived near together, were all suddenly taken away by death.</head>
               <p>Also in <hi>Dorsetshire,</hi> and not far from <hi>Dorchester,</hi> five young men, very eager and hot Conformists, who were newly settled in Livings near each other, were suddenly, and almost altogether, taken away by death: which is very much observed and spoken of by the People in those parts, where it is easie for any one to receive satisfaction a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the truth of the Relation.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:55733:18"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>III.</hi> A Minister heretofore forward for Reformation, and suddenly turned Conformist, was struck with Frenzy and Madness, and remains still in the same condition.</head>
               <p>One Mr. <hi>Allen</hi> a Minister, who had a Living near a Town called <hi>Godliman</hi> in <hi>Surry,</hi> where he was very well accepted amongst the People, and seemed to be very zealous for Reformation against Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perstitious Episcopal Conformity: but being overcome by some temptations, began to Conform; and had no sooner done it, but his Conscience began to fly in his face, and he lay under very great trouble and anguish of Soul, and grew exceeding melancholly, which ended in perfect Distraction, and according to our best information, he continues raving mad to this day, and is become a burden to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self, and a sad spectacle to all his Friends and Acquaintance; but we hope an example to all, to engage them to take heed of the least violation of Conscience, though it be to preserve either life or live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lihood in this world.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>IV.</hi> While a Canonical Parson was upon his knees eating the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secrated Bread, the ground sunk under him, and he fell in up to his middle.</head>
               <p>By Letters bearing date the third of <hi>February</hi> 1661, we are certi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied from very good hands, that not far from <hi>Dorchester,</hi> a Conform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Parson, was, according to the Canon, Celebrating the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Lord's Supper, and while he himself was down upon his knees eating the Consecrated Bread, the ground sunk under him, and he into the same up to his middle, to the astonishment of those three or four Communicants who joyned with him at that time. This is much talked of, and smiled at by many, because it was his Wives Grave which he kneeled somewhat too heavily upon.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>V.</hi> A New-Conformists Wife drowned her self in a Pool.</head>
               <p>Much about the same time, Mistriss <hi>Oake,</hi> the Minister's Wife of <hi>Clifton,</hi> in the County of <hi>Dorset,</hi> who is a New Conformist, leaped into a Pool, and drowned her self: The truth whereof is confirmed
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:55733:18"/> by Letters from Persons of unquestionable Reputation, who are of the Neighborhood.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>VI.</hi> A Minister, heretofore forward for Reformation, while he was Administring the Sacrament according to the Canon, was struck Dumb, and a Gentleman who was chiefly instrumental to perswade him to it, struck with Madness.</head>
               <p>About the beginning of <hi>March</hi> 1661, one Mr. <hi>Johnson</hi> a Minister, who came out of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and was placed at a Town called <hi>Lanckes,</hi> or <hi>Lancras,</hi> near <hi>Biddiford</hi> in the County of <hi>Devon,</hi> was much impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuned by the Parishioners, and more especially by one Mr. <hi>Hutchins</hi> (who did urge him wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h greater violence than all the rest) to Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nister the Sacrament in a promiscuous way, and according to the Cannon. He for a while resisted their importunity, and being a man very much for Reformation, was unwilling to gratifie them in their demands, especially upon the terms which the Parishioners with so much violence insisted on. But at length he was perswaded to do it, and told them, that if they would buy Bread and Wine, he would administer it to them; which accordingly was performed on their part. And when the day came, he proceeded to the Celebration of the Ordinance; and while he was engaged in the work, or immediat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly after, he was smitten Dumb in the place, and so continues to this day: He only makes a noise with his tongue, and seems to be desirous to speak, but cannot. The other Person, <hi>viz.</hi> Mr. <hi>Hutchins,</hi> who was so zealous in the business, was also at the same time bereft of his Senses, and went forth Cursing and Swearing, and remains out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragiously Mad to this day. Such as were eye-witnesses of this sad dispensation, have given us assurance of the truth of it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>VII.</hi> A New Conforming Minister strangely tempted to ride over a poor Woman in the Road, and so to wound her, that within a few dayes after she died.</head>
               <p>In the beginning of <hi>March</hi> 1661, one Mr. <hi>Polewheele,</hi> Minister of <hi>Tavestock,</hi> in the County of <hi>Devon,</hi> a very zealous Non-Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formist, was charged by some violent and malitious Person, for speaking some Treasonable or Seditious words: To appease the Clamour that was hereby made against him, and to pacifie his
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:55733:19"/> Accusers, the next Lord's Day after, he read the Common-Prayer-Book, which, according to his expectation, proved an effectual ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient to attain the end which he proposed to himself in doing of it. But the following Week, this man, upon occasion, Riding from home, over-took a poor Woman travelling on foot upon the Road; when he came up with her, he told her, he <hi>must Ride over her: Ride over me Sir</hi> (said the Woman) <hi>what needs that? the Way is broad enough for us both. That is all one</hi> (said he) <hi>I will ride over thee:</hi> and then set spurs to his Horse and bare her down, and rode over her indeed; and not only so, but gave her several blows with his Staff, whereby she was so hurt and wounded, that within two dayes after the poor Woman died. Whether the Law hath proceeded against him the last Assizes we have not as yet received any certain account.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>VIII.</hi> A New-Conformist upon discontent from what he had done against his Light and Conscience, hanged himself with his Sursingle.</head>
               <p>At a Town called <hi>Kainton,</hi> in the County of <hi>Dorset,</hi> not far from <hi>Sherbourn,</hi> one Mr. <hi>Palmer</hi> was Minister, who through the importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of some of his Acquaintance and Relations, was prevailed with to read the Common-Prayer-Book; but afterward was filled with much horrour of Conscience for it, and spoke to a Friend to go to some Godly People, and intreat them to Pray for him; and withal, signified to him the cause of his trouble: But his terrors and tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions encreasing on him, and falling into the very depth of despon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency and despair, did either speak or send to his Friend to d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>st, and to say nothing of what he had told him; and within a very s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ort time after, <hi>viz.</hi> on the 7th of <hi>March</hi> 1661, did hang himself in his Chamber with his Consecrated Girdle, vulgarly called a <hi>Sursingle.</hi> This sad story is publickly known throughout the Country, and hath much affrighted and astonished many of our late New Conformists in those parts. But some, to palliate the business, have given it out that his troubles did not arise from any sense he had of the evil of Conforming, but because he had lately laid out a great deal of Mony upon a Purchase, which proved to have a very cracked Title, &amp; so was cheated of all his Mony. Whether this be true <hi>de facto</hi> yea or no, is not worthy of a dispute; but that it should be assigned as the cause of his discontent, and of what followed upon it, we can by no means allow, in regard of the sure and undoubted evidence we have of the truth of the whole Relation above-mentioned. However, it is agreed
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:55733:19"/> on all hands that he was a New Conformist, and upon discontent soon after he had practised his Conformity, did hang himself with his Sursingle; which certainly is sufficient to startle any one <hi>whose Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science is not seared with an hot Iron,</hi> that hath offered violence to his Principles, and for <hi>filthy Lucre sake hath received the Mark of the Beast on his Forehead, or in his right hand.</hi> And we hope that this and so many other pregnant instances of the like nature, will be especial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly observed by all the Brethren in the Ministry, who have hitherto kept a good Conscience in that particular, as so many gracious and seasonable warnings from the Lord; yea, as so many certain Sea-marks to direct their course that they may (notwithstanding all their temptation) be preserved from splitting not only their Credit and Reputation, but the peace and comfort of a good Conscience up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that fatal Rock of Conformity.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>IX.</hi> A zealous Non-Conformist, engaging to Administer the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment against his Light, and his former practice; was taken away by death before he could perform his promise.</head>
               <p>In the same Month of <hi>March</hi> 1661, one Mr. <hi>Knight,</hi> a Minister in <hi>Sussex,</hi> a zealous and stiffe Non-Conformist, was by importunity, and for fear of loosing his Place, prevailed with to make a promise that he would in a promiscuous way, contrary to his former practice, give the Sacrament to the whole Parish at Easter following. When the day drew near, he was much perplexed in his mind, and expres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed a great deal of trouble, that he should so far wrong his Conscience as for fear of a little outward loss, to do a thing so vastely disagree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his present Light and former Practice, he languished and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined very much under the sense of his guilt herein, and it pleased the Lord to remove him by a seasonable death, before he had actually discharged his engagement, the thoughts whereof were so bitter and dreadful to him, to the last moment of his life.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>X.</hi> A Prelatical Parson threatning to trouble some honest men in his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rish for not coming to Common-Prayer, was taken away by death before he could effect it.</head>
               <p>Much about the same time, one Mr. <hi>Wilcocks</hi> (a Conforming E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piscopal Parson in <hi>Sussex</hi>) hearing that one in his Parish (whose
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:55733:20"/> Name on purpose we omit) had said, he would not eat any of <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cocks</hi> his Porradge; his meaning was, he would not hear any of his Common-Prayers, did sharply reprove him for using such rude, and defaming words of so holy and perfect a Platform as that was; and withal told him in a menacing way, that before he was a month older he would make him, and all the rest of the Phannatick Non-Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mists in the Parish, come to Divine Service, or suffer the severest Penalties which the Law in that case had provided. But it pleased the Lord, that before the time which he assigned for the execution of his threats was expired, he was seized by a desperate Sickness, which in a short time brought him to his Grave.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>XI.</hi> A debauched Prelatical Parson struck dumb, while he was Preaching, and one side of him smitten with a dead Palsie, and suddenly after died.</head>
               <p>One Mr. <hi>John Buckles,</hi> Parson of <hi>Chester,</hi> about five miles from <hi>Durham,</hi> a man notorious in the Country for Swearing and Drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, with many such other <hi>Prelatical</hi> endowments, did upon the 13th of <hi>April</hi> 1662, Preach in the Cathedral of <hi>Durham,</hi> in the course of one of the Prebends there. His Text was, <hi>Prov.</hi> 24.16. <hi>For a just man falleth seven times, and riseth again; but the wicked shall fall into mischief.</hi> From which Scripture he took occasion to come within the compass of the Prophets <hi>Wo, in calling Evil good, and Good evil;</hi> and accordingly it came upon him: For, before he had fully finished his Sermon, the use of his tongue, and one side of his body was taken away by a dead Palsie (as was conceived) he continued so till the Tuesday following, and then died. This is so notoriously known at <hi>Durham,</hi> that none in the City nor yet in the Bishops Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace, have the face to deny or question it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>XII.</hi> An eminent Schollar Preaching before the King, was, in the beginning of his Sermon, taken with a Qualm, and so forced to break off abruptly.</head>
               <p>Also upon the same 13th day of <hi>April</hi> 1662, one Mr. <hi>South</hi> of <hi>Christs-church</hi> in <hi>Oxford,</hi> and Domestick Chaplain to the Lord Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellour, Preached before the King ar <hi>White-hall.</hi> He being a man of great parts, and learning; a very numerous Assembly came together
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:55733:20"/> to hear him, and it was known before-hand what Subject he intended to handle in that Sermon; For, not long before, he Preached before the Lord Chancellour, and his Lordship being much delighted with his Discourse, made way for him to Preach the same Sermon again before his Majesty: It having first pass'd the Scrutiny of so wise and learned a man, and so great and famous a Counsellour; and having now the Stamp of his <hi>Encomium</hi> upon it, every ones expectation was heightened, and happy was he or she amongst the greatest Wits in the Town, that could accommodate their Humour in getting conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent room in the Chappel, to hang upon the Lips of this so great an Oracle. The fore-mentioned 13th of <hi>April</hi> was the day appointed for the acting of this Scene over again; and doubtless, according to expectation, it must have a very fair Reception now in the Second Edition of it, whose <hi>Exit</hi> before was attended with so signal and great a <hi>Plaudite.</hi> The Service and Anthems being ended, Mr. <hi>South</hi> ascends the Pulpit, the eyes of all were immediately fastened upon him; and after he had performed his obeysance to his Majesty, he names his Text, which was, <hi>Ecclesiastes</hi> 7.10. <hi>Say not thou, What is the cause that the former dayes were better than these? for thou doest not enquire wisely concerning this.</hi> Then, after a witty Preamble, he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds to the division of the words; and having performed that with great dexterity, he layes by his Text for the present, and, according to the Popish-mode, addresses himself to the <hi>Bid-prayer;</hi> which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ended, he resumes his Text, and attempts to handle the several parts of it. The Prohibition in the Text he laboured to enforce by an Induction of particulars. The first was, That the Pagan times were not better than these; then, The Popish times were not, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but the last insisted on, was, The times of the late Rebellion; and while he was endeavouring to evince that, which was indeed the main thing he intended to handle; it pleased God that he was sud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly taken with a Qualm, drops of sweat standing in his face as big as Pease, and immediately he lost the use of his speech, only he ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered some few words to this effect, <hi>Oh Lord! we are all in thy hands, be merciful unto us:</hi> and then came down. The expectations of all being thus sadly disappointed, they were contented with the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertisement of an Anthem, and so the solemnity of the Service for that day was ended.</p>
               <p>In the mean time, great care is taken of Mr. <hi>South,</hi> and by the use of Cordials, and other means proper for him in that condition, he quickly recovers his Spirits, and was every way as well again as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore: And we should be glad to hear he were more sensible of the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:55733:21"/> hand of God upon him at that time, wherein it is to be feared, he sought his own honour more than Christ's, and therefore met with this Rebuke from the Lord, which indeed we would hope in Charity had some good Influence upon him; for the next Lord's day after, he appeared again before the same splendid Auditory, and as we were informed, he did, before-hand, free his Sermon from many of those Luxuriances which before it was attended with, and brings it forth in a less Whorish attire than he had clothed it with the day before; and so, according to our best information, he went on and finished his Discourse without the least disturbance or interruption.</p>
               <p>And we must also further do the Gentleman this right, That he hath formerly been subject to the inconveniencies of such Qualms: For, some years since, when he was appointed to do some Publick Exercise in the <hi>Hall</hi> at <hi>Christs-Church, viz.</hi> to speak a Speech upon some great and signal Occasion: When he had prepared it, and it became every way proportionable to the transcendency of his parts and abilities, he gave it out to several of his Acquaintance, that he intended in that Speech severely to lash the Precisians and Sectaries of the Colledge, and the University also. Which being known a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, and the day wherein he was to perform what he had prepared being now come, it occasioned a great concourse at <hi>Christs-Church-Hall</hi> of the younger Students, who were the greatest Wits, but of the most profligate Principles both in that House, and other Houses in the University. To satisfie all their expectations, Mr. <hi>South</hi> comes forth, and addresses himself with a sufficient measure of Confidence (whereof, by the way, there is no want in him) to speak to this In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genious Auditory: And indeed, the whole Scope of his Oration was little other than a most blasphemous Invective against Godliness, and the most serious and conscientious Professors of it; wherein he had proceeded but a very little way before the hand of the Lord was stretched out against him, and he was suddenly surprized with such a Q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>alm as did disturb him at <hi>White-hall,</hi> so that he was constrained abruptly to break off; Which (being one of so great Fame in the U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niversity for Wit and Parts) he was scarce able to bear, being very sensible how great a disparagement this would be to him among the Wits of his Acquaintance. However, thus much influence it had upon him, that from that time he lay under some Convictions of the evil of abusing those good parts which God had given him in defaming those Persons and things which the Lord doth testifie his greatest ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation of: and so from thence forward he seemed to be much more serious than before, and by degrees insinuated himself into the good
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:55733:21"/> opinion of the then present <hi>Dean,</hi> together with the most famous in that House both for Religion and Learning: So that in a short time he was become a chief and eminent Member of that Society, which he continually before, as he had occasion, threw out his Pasquils a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst. Yea, now as he had opportunity, he laid out his parts to the uttermost, in defence both of the Doctrinal, and Practical part of Religion, and that too, according to the strictest Notion of both of them. In his Publick Sermons at <hi>Maries</hi> (the University Church) he still appeared the great Champion for <hi>Calvinism,</hi> against <hi>Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nianism,</hi> and <hi>Arminianism.</hi> His Carriage was now such, and his Parts so exceeding useful and serviceable, that the Heads of that Party were consulting how to give encouragement to, and accumu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late proportionable Preferments upon so hopeful a Convert: And had not the late Revolution happened as it did, he had doubtless been advanceed to such degrees of Promotion as the Interest of that sort of men could have procured for him, and which his standing in the University did make him capable of. But his Friends falling, he fell with them; and for one whole year at least, after the King came in, he was a Member of the <hi>Phannatick</hi> (he knows what it means) <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary</hi> in <hi>Oxford.</hi> By this time the impressions of his former Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victions being worn out, and the wind of Preferment blowing at a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother door, he knocks hard at it; and if he may be admitted in, he will leave all his <hi>quondam</hi> Friends, renounce his Principles, and lick up his own vomit again, for which he hath met with an early Rebuke from the Lord, and we heartily wish it may be sanctified to him, that he may not dare any more <hi>to kick against the pricks,</hi> nor arm himself against the Almighty, the Rebuke of whose Countenance he is not able one moment to stand before.</p>
               <p>Let the Reader pardon this digression, for it was necessary to be inserted, that the stop which he met with in his Preaching might appear the more considerable, as being a more than ordinary hand of God upon him, who hath thus notoriously prevaricated.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>XIII.</hi> Two debauched Persons rejoyced in the death of Colonel <hi>Barkstead,</hi> and having gotten a piece of his <hi>Liver</hi> out of the fire, carried it to an Alehouse; and when they were almost drunk, would needs eat a piece of it, which they had broyled on the coals; and thereupon both fell desperately sick, and one of them died presently.</head>
               <p>Upon the 19th day of <hi>April</hi> 1662, the day on which Col. <hi>Bark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stead,</hi>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:55733:22"/> Col. <hi>Okey,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Corbet</hi> suffered at Tyburn; amongst the many Thousands who went to see that Execution, there were two men, Inhabitants in <hi>Horsy-Down,</hi> who in an especial manner are to be taken notice of. When they beheld Col. <hi>Barkstead</hi> (whom it seems they had a particular hatred against) in the Cart, they expres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, in a very rude manner their rejoycing, that now they should see him die. They got very near the fire wherein the Bowels were to be burnt, and having a convenient opportunity, did cut off a piece of Col. <hi>Barkstead</hi>'s Liver, and put it up in a Cloth; and when the Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution was finished, they carried this piece of Liver home with them; and in the afternoon, themselves, with some other of their rude Companions, went to an Alehouse to make merry, because, as they said, <hi>the Rogue Barkstead was hanged;</hi> and the piece of Liver which they brought home with them was produced, to heighten their mirth the more. At length, these two fellows drinking themselves almost drunk, began to be very extravagant, and resolved they would eat up this piece of Col. <hi>Barkstead</hi>'s Liver; and accordingly prepared it for the Coals, then laid it on and broyled it, and then did eat up a good part, if not all of it: upon which, they both immediately fell desperately sick, and within a few hours one of them died: and the other not like to continue long in the world. This Relation is suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently attested by the Neighbourhood, who will give satisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to any that will enquire after it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>XIV.</hi> One who was Painting the Queens Chappel, was killed by a fall from a Scaffold.</head>
               <p>Upon the 16th of <hi>April</hi> 1662, when the Chappel at <hi>Jamses</hi> was preparing for the new Queen, one of the Artists, who was at Work there in Painting the Roof of it, fell down from the Scaffold; and of that fall immediately died.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>XV.</hi> A Constable, who was forward to Present his Neighbors for not co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to their Parish Church, being afterwards troubled in Conscience for it, drowned himself in a Pond.</head>
               <p>By Order from the Justices at the Quarter-Sessions holden in the East Riding of <hi>York-shire;</hi> about the Month of <hi>April</hi> 1662, the Constables were enjoyned to Present, and bring in a List of the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:55733:22"/> Names of all such Persons as came not to their Parish Churches. For this purpose, the chief Constables of the several Divisions, sent out their Warrants to the Petty-Constables, requiring them to make Return accordingly. One of the said Warrants came to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stables of <hi>Hollam</hi> in <hi>Holderness,</hi> the one of which was unwilling to Present his Neighbors as was required: but the other was very zeal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and forward in the work, and made a Return of the Names of about twelve Persons, who out of Conscience could not joyn with the Parish Worship. Presently after he had done this, his Consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence began to be much troubled for it; and the remembrance of it wrought such disquietness in his mind, as forced him to make sad complaints to his Relations about it: and when he could find no ease that way, he went to his fellow Constable, and acquainted him with his trouble, together with the cause of it, desiring him to try if he could get the List of the Names which he had Returned, with-drawn; and promised him twenty shillings upon his effecting of it. But in that, his desires could not be satisfied: upon which, the anguish of his Soul was far greater than before, neither knew he which way to ease himself. For some dayes he continued thus in a very restless state, and Satan (who alway watches his opportunity to do mischief) began to tempt him to desperate courses. His Relations being afraid thereof, kept a continual watch over him; and one time his Son pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented him when he was about to drown himself. But his perplexed Conscience haunted him like a Ghost, which through Satan's sug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gestions did soon precipitate him into destruction: For many dayes did not pass over his head, before he got an opportunity to throw himself into a Pond, where he miserably ended his life. The truth of this very sad Relation, is publickly known and attested; and we hope will be a warning to all that hear of it, to take heed how they gratifie the Devil in doing his drudgery, lest he make a prey of them in the conclusion. And we are certainly informed, that many Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stables, who live in those parts where this sad Tragedy was acted, do make that use of it, and are warned by the example of this poor man, to avoid the Rock upon which he split his Soul.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>XVI.</hi> A wicked Woman killed by a Thunder-clap: with an Account of other mischiefs done by the same.</head>
               <p>Upon the 3d of <hi>May</hi> 1662, there happened a dreadful Storm of Thunder, at a Town called <hi>Cundle-Purse,</hi> in the County of <hi>Dorset,</hi>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:55733:23"/> on the Border of <hi>Sommerset-shire,</hi> where lived one <hi>Dorothy Chapman,</hi> a Woman of very ill Fame in respect of her Conversation. She was noted for Cursing, and using very sad Imprecations upon any slight occasions. The outer-door of this Womans house was strangely thrown open by this Storm; and while she was in the house with her three Children, one of which was suddenly cast under the Table, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother thrown down, and the third carried from the fire-side and thrown down in the middle of the house: the Woman her self siting before the fire, was struck dead; her clothes down to the waste were very much rent and torn; much of her hair torn from her head, and thrown about the house; her head-clothes could not be found ever after; the glass and bars of a window broken out: there was also in a Chamber one of the boards, which was fast nailed, blown up, and then nailed down again; the house was very much rent and torn, both within and without; and nothing all this while seen in the house but smoke, which was accompanied with the smell of brimstone.</p>
               <p>This whole Relation comes from <hi>Leonard Chapman,</hi> Husband to the Woman, and her eldest Son; they have left the house upon it, and are afraid to live any longer in it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>XVII.</hi> A Trooper, who gave out threatning speeches against a godly Non-Conforming Minister, killed by his fellow Trooper in a quarrel.</head>
               <p>Much about the same time, one of the Troop which was then Quartered at <hi>Hertford,</hi> did very much threaten a Godly Minister in that Town, for not reading the Common-Prayer; and gave out speeches, that he would do him some great mischief if he neglected to Conform any longer. It pleased the Lord, that soon after this, upon a quarrel between this Souldier and one of his fellow Troopers, that he was openly in the face of the whole Town, run thorow by him, and died immediately. He that murdered him made his escape presently, and according to our best information hath not since been heard of. This is related by credible Persons, Inhabitants of <hi>Hert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> who are able to make the truth of it to appear, to any that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sires satisfaction about it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>XVIII.</hi> Two of the King's Servants prophaning the Lord's Day, were taken away by untimely death.</head>
               <p>Upon the first of <hi>June</hi> 1662, being the Lord's Day, one of the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:55733:23"/> King's houshold, not remembring the fourth Commandment, which doth enjoyn all to <hi>keep holy the Sabbath day,</hi> would use his Recreation that day: and going to Swim in the River near <hi>Hampton Court,</hi> he was there drowned. Another of his fellow Servants spending that day as vainly and unprofitably as the other, was also upon the same first of <hi>June</hi> run over by a Coach, and killed out-right immediately.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>XIX.</hi> One of the King's Life-guard struck dumb and lame, while he was upon his knees at Mass in the Queens Chappel.</head>
               <p>On the 5th of <hi>June</hi> 1662, one of the King's Life-guard invited and perswaded his Comrade, to go along with him into the Queens Chappel, at <hi>Hampton Court,</hi> to see the fashion of their Mass-Service; upon which, they both went into the Chappel together, and were no sooner entred, but either at the Elevation of the Hoast, or some other very weighty occasion, all the Worshippers fell suddenly down upon their knees. He that was so forward to see fashions, advised with his Comrade, whether it were not civility in them to kneel al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so, who expressed much unwillingness to do it; but the other imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately kneeled down as the rest did, and while he was yet upon his knees, the hand of the Lord smote him: for his speech was quite taken away, and he was dead on one side of his body; and by the help of his Comrade, and some others that were present, was car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried out of the Chappel, and by his Majesties Command was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyed presently to <hi>Kingston,</hi> and committed to the Cure of Doctor <hi>Bates,</hi> who hath his abode there. So far as we can learn he is yet alive, but continues dumb and lame to this day. These two last par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars are so publickly known, that they need none of our confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>XX.</hi> A Constables house burnt down to the ground, and the fire by a strange wind driven from an honest mans house, whom the Constable had a little before molested, and persecuted, for his Conscience sake.</head>
               <p>Much about the time last mentioned, at a place called <hi>Fordenbridge</hi> in <hi>Hampshire,</hi> several of the Inhabitants there, meeting with no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that tended to their Edification or Comfort in the Publick; betook themselves to Private Meetings: The Constable of the Town, an Inn-keeper, and one of a most vicious and debauched Conversation, having notice thereof, immediately went to the house
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:55733:24"/> where they were peaceably met to Worship God, and apprehends them all, and carries them before a Justice of Peace; who bound them over to answer it at the Assizes or Sessions. The same night there appeared and was seen by some credible Persons, a stream of Fire in the Air, directly pointing upon this Constables house, and by the next morning his house was fired, and was burnt down to the ground with about thirteen houses more in the Town. And when the fire came to the house of one of those honest men who were pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secuted by the Constable, there arose upon a sudden, a very strong Wind, which beat the fire from his house, and so little or no damage was done to it. This Relation (although so strange, and amongst some Persons almost incredible) hath been so often confirmed, and that too by unquestionable hands, who are upon the place, that we do with much confidence assert it as a great Truth; and also a most emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent and signal Providence, sufficient to startle the greatest Zealots at this day, who drive on so furiously in disturbing and molesting the Religious and peaceable Meetings of honest men, who cannot with a good Conscience frequent the Publick Assemblies, nor joyn with the Worship that is there Celebrated.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>XXI.</hi> A New-Conformist withered in his Gifts grew sottish, not able to Preach, and then died.</head>
               <p>At a Town called <hi>Bradford,</hi> in the County of <hi>Dorset,</hi> and about two miles from <hi>Dorchester,</hi> was settled one Mr. <hi>Toope,</hi> the Minister there. He was a man much for Reformation; but of late was strange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly overcome to read the Service-Book, and to practice some other Canonical Conformity against his present Light, and former Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessions: which, the Lord did with a severe hand visit upon him, for immediately after his Parts did visibly decline and wither; at length, he grew altogather sottish, and was not able to Preach at all; and about the 25th of <hi>June</hi> 1662, was taken away by death. This is pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly known to be true, and very much noted by all the observing People in those parts.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>XXII.</hi> A debauched Person rejoycing in the death of Sir <hi>Henry Vane,</hi> vomitted up blood till he died.</head>
               <p>A rude and debauched Person, who lived at the <hi>Goat Tavern</hi> in <hi>Olaves Southwark,</hi> did much rejoyce at the death of Sir <hi>Henry Vane,</hi>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:55733:24"/> who was executed on Tower-Hill, <hi>June</hi> the 14th 1662, on which morning he was heard to say with much joy, That he would go see the <hi>blessed stroak given.</hi> It pleased the Lord, that not many dayes after, this man died vomitting up nothing but blood. This is suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently attested by Persons of good Reputation, who were of his Neighbourhood.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>XXIII.</hi> A Youth who had stollen some Goods, was taken hold of by an evil Spirit, raised by a Conjurer, who brought him over hedge and ditch, hills and houses, to the place where the Goods were lost.</head>
               <p>At the <hi>Greyhound-Inn</hi> in <hi>Blandford,</hi> in the County of <hi>Dorset,</hi> were stoln some Goods of a considerable value: they were laid to the charge of a Servant in the house, who being not able to bear the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den of so foul an imputation, went to a Conjurer, who by the help of an Evil Spirit, in a strange and dreadful manner, brought forth him who had indeed stoln the Goods away. It proved to be the Son of one <hi>Violet,</hi> a Shoomaker in that Town, whose Boy was then at <hi>Bristol,</hi> fifty miles from <hi>Blandford:</hi> but the Evil Spirit brought him o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver hedge and ditch, and sometimes thorow the water, and over hills and houses; and at last left him on the top of a Wood-pile in <hi>Bland<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> where he lay crying out, That the Devil was at his back, and had fastened his claw in it. His Friends hearing of this, fetch'd him home: The whole Town is wonderfully affrighted; he confes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth the Theevery of his own accord; but he is still haunted, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause he brought not the Goods back again: they carried him to bed, and locked him up into a Chamber, and the door being shut, he was fetched away again about midnight, <hi>June</hi> 25. and carried they know not whither. This is a thing so publickly known, that the whole Countrey rings of it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>XXIV.</hi> A Prelatical Priest Preaching up, and magnifying the Episcopal Cause, was immediately struck with death.</head>
               <p>About the latter end of <hi>June,</hi> or beginning of <hi>July</hi> 1662, one Mr. <hi>Steer,</hi> the Episcopal Priest of <hi>Staly</hi> near <hi>Chesterfield,</hi> in the County of <hi>Derby:</hi> upon a very solemne occasion was appointed to Preach at <hi>Chesterfield,</hi> before the <hi>Arch-Deacon.</hi> The scope of his Discourse was to shew how the Episcopal Cause <hi>had been dead and buried, yea, a seal had been set upon the Sepulchre, yet this Cause had a glorious Resurrection,</hi> &amp;c. The words were scarce out of his mouth, before death arrested him,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:55733:25"/> he only lived to finish this Royal Testimony, and then immediately gave up the Ghost.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>XXV.</hi> Two men, very great opposers of a Godly Presbyterian Minister, were killed by Dogs.</head>
               <p>At a Town called <hi>Brampton,</hi> about two miles from <hi>Chesterfield</hi> aforesaid, lived one Mr. <hi>Thomas Watts,</hi> and one <hi>Godfry Swift;</hi> two principal men of that Town. These two were most malitious ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to one Mr. <hi>Moor,</hi> the Godly Minister of that place, who being of the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> perswasion, did hold fast his Principles, and would by no means practise the least part of Canonical Conformity; for which reason only, these men did express themselves upon all oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casions, with great bitterness against him. One of them, <hi>viz.</hi> Mr. <hi>Watts,</hi> did publickly say, <hi>That he would make Mr.</hi> Moor <hi>read the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice-Book, or else it should cost him his life.</hi> Not long after he had ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered that malitious and threatning speech, it pleased the Lord, that as he was riding upon his Horse, in the Town where he lived, a Dog came forth, and made his Horse start, and throw him; of which fall he immediately died.</p>
               <p>The other being in the Shambles at <hi>Chesterfield,</hi> a Dog running at a Hog, forced the Hog to run between his legs, and threw him down; of which fall he also immediately died. These two last particulars, are fully testified, by credible Persons of the Neighbourhood, where these remarkable Providences happened.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>XXVI.</hi> A zealous promoter of Prelatical Ceremonies, provides a Book of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Prayer, and a Surplice for the Non-Conforming Minister of his own Town: and as he was coming home with them, his Horse threw him in a shallow Water, and he was drowned.</head>
               <p>At a Town called <hi>Malton</hi> in <hi>Devonshire,</hi> lived one <hi>Hunt</hi> (accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to our best information, that was his Name) who was a great Zealot for the Service-Book, and Ceremonies. He often urged the Godly Minister of the place, to Conform, but could not prevail: Whereupon he resolves to tender him the Common-Prayer-Book, and the Surplice together, on a Lord's day, which he had designed for that purpose; and, in order thereto, goes to <hi>Exeter,</hi> and provides both these engines; intending to make great use of them towards the removal of the Non-Conforming Minister. But the Lord was
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:55733:25"/> pleased wonderfully to prevent him; for upon the Saturday, as he was coming from <hi>Exeter,</hi> with his Common-Prayer-Book and Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plice, he rode into a shallow stream, where his Horse fell with him: and whether he was disguised with drink, or no, we cannot certainly say; but in that shallow Water, which did not reach to the knees of the Horse, he was drowned; and also his Common-Prayer-Book, and Surplice, throughly washed against the next day. This is a story no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious in those parts.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>XXVII.</hi> A New Conformist left of God to fall into a grosse scandalous sin, afterwards grows melancholy, leaves his Relations, and is not since heard of.</head>
               <p>Also in the same County of <hi>Devon,</hi> an eminent Non-Conforming Minister, not far from <hi>Exeter,</hi> (whose Name for some reasons we purposely conceal) going to Preach at a Town not far from him, where the Common-Prayer-Book was much adored; and would at no time be satisfied, except it were read amongst them: A Person of Quality knowing this, and fearing lest this Minister should be brought into a snare by his going thither, did much diswade him from it; but when he could not prevail, he urged him to give him his engagement, that if he did go, he would not read the Common-Prayer, or else, told him, he would not lend him his Horse (which he desired then to borrow of him) to carry him to the place. The Minister passes his word to hin accordingly: But when he came there, contrary to his so fresh engagement, and to his former Principles and Practice, he was prevailed with to read the Book; and not only so, but (there being occasion for it) he Churches a Woman, and Baptizes a Child with the sign of the Cross, according to the Form prescribed in the Book. When he had done all this, God left him, to commit imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately a publick scandalous sin. For, as he was returning home, he fell into a blind Alehouse by the way, not far from his home (a place which he abhorred to come near before) and there, meeting with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauched Company, he drinks himself drunk, and became the May-game amongst them. In this case he comes home, and was the won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derment of the whole Family, having not at any time before been thus over-taken. He was, at his first coming in, very apish and ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diculous, but afterwards grew outragious, and took a very slight oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion to beat his Wife, and to commit some other extravagances of like nature. The next morning, after he had slept, he began to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider of the passages that happened the day and night before, and fell
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:55733:26"/> into a deep Melancholy: and immediately left his Relations, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted none of them whither he intended to go; and what is since become of him, we can give for the present no satisfactory account. This is attested by Persons of Quality in those parts, who have suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient reason to know the certain truth of the premises.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>XXVIII.</hi> A New Conformist being in great troubles of Conscience, drowned himself in his own Well.</head>
               <p>At a Town called (according to our best information) <hi>Wich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hampton,</hi> betwixt <hi>Winburne</hi> and <hi>Blandford,</hi> in the County of <hi>Dorset,</hi> was settled as Minister, one Mr. <hi>Tayler,</hi> who had taken the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, and was a Friend to Reformation; but he was drawn by some carnal Reasons and Motives, to Conform, wherein he proceeded gradually, till at last he arrived at Cathedral Conformity, reading Second Service at the Altar, in all postures. Some Godly Ministers taking notice of it, went to him, and argued with him about his Practice. At last he expressed a great deal of trouble for what he had done, and began by degrees to relinquish some parts of his Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity; First, he waved going up to the Altar, and performed the whole Service in the Desk; afterward, his Melancholy still en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creasing, he left off some grosser and more offensive parts of the Common-Prayer: then his trouble growing yet more upon him, he totally laid the Book aside; and last of all his Preaching also: And presently upon it, on a Lord's day in the morning, about the 13th of <hi>July</hi> 1662, he arose early, and told his Wife he would go down and drink; but being in great horrours of Conscience, he cast himself into his Well, with his head foremost, and was immediately drown'd. There is very great talk of this sad dispensation of the Lord, toward this poor man and his Family, and it is by all received as a certain Truth, which none in those parts have the confidence to contradict.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="29" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>XXIX.</hi> Two men killed by the fall of some part of the Walls of <hi>Coventry,</hi> and the Earl of <hi>Northampton</hi> his only Son, Child, and Heir died while his Lordship was engaged in demolishing those Walls.</head>
               <p>The Earl of <hi>Northampton</hi> having received Order from his Superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours, to pull down and demolish those ancient and famous Walls of
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:55733:26"/> the City of <hi>Coventry,</hi> and being very much quickened thereunto by a Letter which he afterwards received from his Grace, the Duke of <hi>Albermarle</hi> (that known and most constant Asserter of his Countries Liberties) did, towards the latter end of <hi>July</hi> 1662, with great vigor and earnestness fall upon that work, which we must not in the least question, but that it was highly pleasing to the Citizens, who being now eased of the burden of repair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and keeping up their Walls, and maintaining the Mounds of their<note n="*" place="margin">A Cōmon which the City hath injoyed for many years, and was an extraordinary relief to their Poor, but was lately given away from them by his Majesty, to a Courtier that begged it.</note> Park, do look upon themselves as perfectly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered from the Tyranny, and Slavery under which they groaned, during the Reign of the former Usurpers; and now though they have lost their Walls, yet they fear not (as they did in the times of the late Rebellion and Usurpation) the pulling down of their Cross, which is likely to do them shortly more Service with his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liness than their Walls would ever have done, though his Lordship had spared them, which he would not do by any means, but pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded in that honourable employment, till two men were killed out-right, and many wounded in the work, and until News came to his Lordship on the 3d of <hi>August</hi> 1662, that his only Son, Heir, and Child was taken away by death; so that the Extinction of his Lordships Family bears date from the Destruction of the Walls of <hi>Coventry,</hi> as <hi>Hiels</hi> did on the contrary from the building of the Walls and setting up the Gates of <hi>Jericho,</hi> according to the Word of the Lord.</p>
               <p>And now his Lordship having neither Wife nor Child, it is hoped that he will settle his Estate upon the City of <hi>Coventry;</hi> that if ever hereafter it shall consist with the safety and preservation of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment to have Walled Towns again in <hi>England, Coventry</hi> may have some Foundation to re-build hers upon.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="30" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>XXX.</hi> The Major of <hi>Cambridge</hi> (heretofore an eminent active man for the Parliament) did against his Conscience, take the new Oaths enjoyned by the late Act for Regulating of Corporations; and within few dayes after died.</head>
               <p>About the lattet end of <hi>July</hi> 1662, the Commissioners appointed for Regulating of Corporations, did, in pursuance of the late Act
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:55733:27"/> for that purpose, come to the Town of <hi>Cambridge,</hi> and calling the Magistrates together, did propound the taking of the Oaths enjoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by that Act; in the first place to Alderman <hi>French,</hi> who was the present Major, and heretofore one of the most active men in the Parliaments Cause in that part of <hi>England.</hi> After a few Arguments used by the Commissioners to perswade him to give a good example to the rest of his Brethren, by his ready complyance; he was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed with against his Principles and Conscience to satisfie their importunity, and took the Oaths enjoyned by that Act; expecting that now he should be continued in his place, and serve out his time as Major. But he had no sooner sworn, but presently, for some rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of State, the Commissioners turned him out, and made him un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capable of being Major or Alderman any longer in that Corporation. The sense of what he had done, and the unexpected usuage he met with from the Commissioners so wrought upon him, and did bring him into so deep a Melancholy and discontent, that within a few dayes after he miserably ended his life.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="31" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>XXXI.</hi> The Archbishop of <hi>Ireland</hi> thrown by his Horse, as he was at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending the Lord Lieutenant to Church.</head>
               <p>By Letters from very considerable Persons in <hi>Ireland,</hi> we are cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified, that on the first Lord's day the Lord Lieutenant went to Church after his arrival at <hi>Dublin</hi> (which was about the 3d of <hi>August</hi> 1662.) his Lordship was attended in very great state by the Lords Spiritual and Temporal on horse-back, and amongst them appeared as Magnificent as any, the Right Reverend Arch-Bishop of <hi>Armath,</hi> Doctor <hi>Brommell:</hi> but his Lordships horse it seems being better fed than taught, in absolute Contempt of the holy Function, with a very scornful eye looked upon his Rider, and gave his Lordship a most dangerous fall in the Presence of his Grace the Duke of <hi>Ormond,</hi> and his noble Attendants. The Arch-Bishop (a known Lover of clean Linnen) was forced to return back, and get his Lawn sleeves wash<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed before he could pay his attendance to the Lord Lieutenant; by which means the Solemnity of that dayes Procession was most unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily interrupted. Strange Observations were made of this Fall of the Bishop in his Pontificalibus, by some foolish Phannatick People, who look upon this as a more cleer and emphatical Prognostick of the downfal of the Hiererchy, than the fall of Arch-Bishop <hi>Laud</hi>'s Picture in the former times.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="32" type="section">
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:55733:27"/>
               <head>XXXII. One who was very active in burning the Solemn League and Covenant, was himself burn'd, by a Fire which kindled in his own house, and consumed it to the ground.</head>
               <p>Letters from very credible Persons, Inhabitants of <hi>Bridgwater,</hi> in the County of <hi>Sommerset,</hi> do assure us, that one in that Town was the last year extreamly active in burning the Solemn League and Covenant, and was the Ring-leader of the Rabble that offered vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence to it. It pleased the Lord, that on the 3d of <hi>August</hi> 1662, at night, this mans house was set on fire and consumed by it, and him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self also burn'd in his bed; of which remarkable Providence and Judgment the whole Town hath taken great notice, and made their Observations upon it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="33" type="section">
               <head>XXXIII. A Ministers hand (as he was attempting to subscribe) taken with so great a trembling, that he was not able to write his Name.</head>
               <p>From very credible Persons we are informed, that one Mr. <hi>Bowden,</hi> Minister of <hi>Ashburton,</hi> in the County of <hi>Sommerset</hi> or <hi>Devon,</hi> being in his Judgment utterly against Conformity, was yet by the earnest importunities of some very near Relations, prevailed with, to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>company some of his Neighbour Ministers to the Ordinary of the Diocess, with a full purpose (though against many checks of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science) to Conform; but when his turn came to Subscribe before the Ordinary, he took up the Pen and attempted to write, but his hand was suddenly taken with such a trembling (which he was, as we hear, never before subject to) that he was not able to write his Name, he attempted to do it several times, but still his hand so shoke that he could not; then one offered to help him by guiding his hand; but his answer was, <hi>That he would not tempt God any further;</hi> and so threw away the Pen, and kept his Conscience whole.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="34" type="section">
               <head>XXXIV. A New Conformist strangely pelted with stones.</head>
               <p>By Letters from very credible Persons in the West of <hi>England,</hi> we are certainly informed, that one Mr. <hi>How,</hi> Minister of <hi>Thorn-falcon,</hi> in the County of <hi>Sommerset,</hi> was a violent Stickler against Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, and (as it is reported) he often said, <hi>He would rather be
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:55733:28"/> stoned to death, than Conform.</hi> But afterwards, upon some unworthy account (as it is feared) he did against his Light, Conscience, and former Professions, and Protestations, <hi>receive the mark of the Beast;</hi> but before a Lord's day came about, after he had thus declined and bawked his Principles, it pleased God, that a great company of stones were thrown into the room where he was, by an invisible hand, thorow the windows: he sent out one to see who threw them, but none could be found; yet still the stones came flying in very fast, till at length he caused his window-shuts to be put to, to keep the stones from fly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in; and then they came as fast down at a Jack-hole, or Clock-hole. Thus it continued for several days together, &amp; then ceased; afterwards the stones were thrown in again for some few dayes, and then ceased. What effect this strange Providence hath had upon this mans spirit, and whether these stones have broken his hardened heart, and made him sensible of the proportion which this Judgment holds with his sin, we have as yet received no certain information; only we pray the Lord that he may repent, and give glory to God, lest the stones at last (according to his own imprecation) do execution upon him, as they did upon <hi>Achan,</hi> because of the Wedge of Gold, and the goodly <hi>Babylonish</hi> Garment, which were found in his Tent.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="35" type="section">
               <head>XXXV. A Church-Warden, who went to the Bishops Visitation to Present some honest Non-Conformists, was in his return (being in drink) killed by a fall from his Horse.</head>
               <p>On the 17th and 18th of <hi>September</hi> 1662, the Bishop's Visitation was held at <hi>Beverly,</hi> in the County of <hi>York,</hi> where one <hi>John Stevens,</hi> a Wine-Cooper by Trade, and a Church-Warden in <hi>Hull,</hi> did Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent several honest and peaceable Non-Conformists there, who on the Lord's dayes did use to meet, to Worship God, at a place called <hi>Cowescots,</hi> about half a mile from <hi>Hull.</hi> This <hi>Stevens</hi> having done his and the Devils work, did, on the 18th of <hi>September,</hi> return back to <hi>Hull,</hi> and being much in drink (the ordinary Guise of those who bring Grist to the Bishop's Mill) he fell several times from his Horse by the way, and was thereby exceedingly bruised. But contrary to the perswasions and entreaties of some of his Friends, he would still go forward, till at last he had so desperate a fall from his Horse, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat he lived but one night, and never spoke one sensible wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d after it. The truth of this is sufficiently known, and much spoken of in all those parts where it happened.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="36" type="section">
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:55733:28"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>XXXVI.</hi> A New-Conformist taken away by death, immediately upon his Conforming.</head>
               <p>In <hi>Martins</hi>-lane, near <hi>Cannon-street,</hi> in the City of <hi>London,</hi> was placed as Minister, one Mr. <hi>Swinnock,</hi> who was also Chaplain lately to one of the <hi>Sheriffs</hi> of the City; he seemed to be a great Zealot against Conformity, and (as ear-witnesses, who are Persons both of Credit and Quality, have affirmed) he hath often said, <hi>He would ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther burn, than Conform;</hi> and did wish, <hi>he might be burnt if he did Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form,</hi> or words to the same effect. This man (as it is upon too just grounds feared) for filthy Lucre's sake, did at last accompany the rest of the Herd, and to save his Living, lost his Principles; he did all that was to be done by the 24th of <hi>August</hi> last past; and then the Bishop of <hi>London</hi> (another lover of clean linnen) Commands him, and the rest of his Lordships <hi>Black Guard,</hi> to be Clothed in <hi>White,</hi> and to wear the Surplice duly, upon Pain of Suspention at least. Mr. <hi>Swinnock</hi> was at first much troubled, and this Garment was somewhat too big for his Conscience; but at length, by the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swasions of some of his Brethren <hi>Revolters</hi> (a Tribe profound to make slaughter both of the Souls and Bodies of men) he resolves to put it on; and accordingly did so on the 21 of <hi>September</hi> 1662, And while this holy Vestment was yet on his back, it pleased the Lord to strike him with Sickness, which proved a violent burning Feavour, whereof within a few dayes after, before another Lord's day came about, he died. What the frame of his Spirit was on his death-bed, or whether the Distemper did so violently seize upon him as to take away his Senses, we shall forbear to give any account: only in Charity, we hope God gave him Repentance unto Life; and we wish that his Example may be seriously and timously laid to heart by those who yet persist in their Apostacy, lest whilst out of God's way they seek to save their Livings, by his righteous and just hand they lose both Living and Life also.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="37" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>XXXVII.</hi> A Woman, whose Husband was a great Persecutor of Non-Conformists, delivered of a strange Birth.</head>
               <p>About the 23d of <hi>October</hi> 1662, the Wife of one <hi>Phillip Miller</hi> in St. <hi>Johns-street,</hi> near <hi>Smithfield-Barrs,</hi> was delivered of a very
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:55733:29"/> strange Birth. The Eyes stood very far out of the Head, and the Ears were only a piece of flesh rolled up together, and an hole in the middle of it; It had no Pallat of the Mouth, and but some little part of a Tongue: It was lame from the Elbow down-ward to the Hands, and the Hands were crooked like the hands of a <hi>Changeling,</hi> and there lacked one Finger of each Hand. The Feet also were lame, and very imperfect, there being but one Toe upon one foot, and but two Toes on the other. The Child lived but three or four dayes, and then died. This is to a Circumstance attested by several credible Persons who were at the Womans Labour, and were eye-witnesses thereof. But that which makes this Providence the more remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, is, That the Father of this Child is a very debauched Person, yet a <hi>true Son</hi> of the <hi>Episcopal Church,</hi> a desperate Blasphemer and Rayler against the power of Godliness, and the sincere Professours thereof: one that usually spends the Lord's day in hunting after pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Meetings of religious, and peaceable Non-Conformists; and hath been very forward and active in seizing many of them, and haling them to Prisons meerly for Conscience sake.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="38" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>XXXVIII.</hi> A Superstitious Priest strangely confounded, and non-plus'd by an immediate hand of God, while he was Preaching.</head>
               <p>Since the turning out of the Reverend Doctor <hi>Spurstow</hi> (that emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Gospel-Preacher) from his place at <hi>Hackney,</hi> in the County of <hi>Middlesex;</hi> the Bishop of <hi>London</hi> hath put in to Officiate there, a most Superstitious, Pragmatical, Persecuting Priest, who upon the 9th of <hi>November</hi> 1662, being the Lord's day, did Preach in the morning at <hi>Hackney</hi> from that Scripture, <hi>Psal.</hi> 62.11. <hi>God hath spoken once, twice have I heard this, that Power belongeth unto God.</hi> In the close of his Sermon, for that part of the day, he bespake the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples Attendance upon him again in the afternoon, intimating to them, that he intended to make some further Progress in his Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course on that Text: And withal, did endeavour to heighten their expectations with many foolish and vain-glorious expressions of what wonders he intended to do in the afternoon: which were very Nau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seous and Offensive to the most sober and discreet part of the Audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory. But he had proceeded but a very little way in his afternoon-Sermon, before the Lord struck him, that he was not able to speak a word of sense, but repeated things over and over, seven, eight, or ten times; yea, some expressions he used almost twenty times over
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:55733:29"/> one after another, so that he was wholly confounded, and not able to proceed in his work, but came down and made his Apology to the People, which he did rationally, and to the satisfaction of many of the Hearers. But when he attempted to go on with his Sermon, he was wholly bereft of his understanding and memory, and was very ridiculous in all that he spake: He seemed, at present, with tears to own the hand of God against him, and to be much affected with it, and begged the Peoples Prayers, <hi>that God would sanctifie it to him, and shew him his mind in it.</hi> But by his carriage since, we have too much cause to fear that that rebuke from God hath not had that effectual o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration upon him, which we pray it may have, if the Lord so please: However this remarkable Providence did evince the truth in the Text, better than any thing that was spoken from it that day; which certainly the Lord would have the People to attend to, and make their observations from.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="39" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>XXXIX.</hi> A drunken Parson found dead in a ditch.</head>
               <p>One <hi>Huson,</hi> a notorious drunken Priest, every way qualified for Preferment under the present Reformation, hath been put into two good Livings near St. <hi>Neots,</hi> in the County of <hi>Huntingdon.</hi> And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at St. <hi>Neots</hi> Market, on the 13th of <hi>November</hi> 1662, did with some others of his Orthodox Brethren (for the satisfaction of the People, that they were none of those scandalous Ministers who were turned out of their Livings on the 24th of <hi>August</hi> last, for being guilty of one of the Seven deadly Sins, <hi>viz. Non-Conformity</hi>) fall to drinking very hard, till Parson <hi>Huson</hi> was so drunk, that going home that Night, he fell from his Horse into a Ditch, wherein was little or no Water; and being in that condition, was not able to help him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self, but remained in the Ditch all night, and was there found dead the next morning.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="40" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>XL.</hi> A man who bitterly swore against and cursed his Horses, was found dead in the High-way, and his Horses also lying dead by him.</head>
               <p>Upon the 21 of <hi>November</hi> 1662, one <hi>Harpar,</hi> an Inhabitant of the Town of <hi>Bedford,</hi> went with a Load of Corn to <hi>Shefford</hi> Market, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout seven miles from <hi>Bedford;</hi> and having sold his Corn, he loaded his Cart home again with raw Hides; and when he was come about three miles back from <hi>Shefford</hi> (the Wayes being very bad) his Cart was Set; upon that, he swore against and cursed his Cattel
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:55733:30"/> most bitterly, and wished them dead. An honest man, who was not far from him, came to him, and having reproved him for his Swearing and Cursing, help'd him out with his Cart. He had not gone much further, but his Cart was Set again, and he, as before, cursed his Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, and used many strange Imprecations against them: The honest man assisted him again, and got out his Cart the second time; but with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al told him, That because of his dreadful Cursing and Swearing he would no longer stay with him, and so went home to his house, which was not far off. The next morning, a little way from the place where the Cart was Set the night before, the Phill-Horse was found dead with the Cart-saddle on his back, and the Cart standing not far from him: and about half a mile nearer <hi>Bedford,</hi> at a place called <hi>Hammer-Hill,</hi> in the Parish of <hi>Cardington,</hi> the man was found dead lying on his face upon the ground, in the common High-way; and very near him lay his other three Horses, in their Cart-geeres, dead also. A Man and a Boy, who were with him, wandred up and down a good part of the evening, till they came to an house which stood alone and uninha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited, where they sheltered themselves till morning; but both fell desperately ill upon it: and 'tis reported that one of them is since dead. The truth of this whole Relation in the several circumstances of it, is notoriously and publickly known in those parts, as any man will find, who will take the pains to enquire after it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="41" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>XLI.</hi> The High Altar in Trinity Colledge Chappel, in the University of Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge, with all the rich Furniture belonging to it, consumed by fire.</head>
               <p>On the 30th of <hi>November,</hi> being <hi>Advent Sunday,</hi> a very sad accident came to the <hi>High Altar,</hi> newly errected in <hi>Trinity Colledge Chappel</hi> in <hi>Cambridge,</hi> which according to the information we have received by divers Letters written from some of the Fellows of that House, was as followeth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Even song being ended, the Chappel Clerk put up the Candles-ends in a Box; and not being careful enough in extinguishing them, and placing the Box very irreverently too near the</hi> Sanctum Sanctorum, <hi>it took fire, which was</hi> so prophane <hi>as to burn down the Traverse, which was made of most rich</hi> Mosaick-<hi>work, and the new Errected Altar, with all the costly Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niture wherewith it was Adorned, which were all sacrificed in the flames: Yea, it spared not the Book of</hi> Common Prayer, <hi>which lay upon it, nor the</hi> holy Vestments <hi>belonging to the Choristers and Singing-men, nor the</hi> Consecrated Plate, <hi>not only that which was then upon the Altar, but a
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:55733:30"/> great Chest of other Chappel Plate also;</hi> which (as most of the Letters say) was melted. But all agree, it was most Sacrilegiously by some seeming Friends (who came with a pretence to endeavour the quenching of the fire) stollen away, and not an ounce of it saved. One Circumstance is most remarkable in this Accident, <hi>viz.</hi> That this High Altar was the first that was set up in <hi>Cambridge,</hi> yea, as it is believed in all <hi>England</hi> since the late Revolution; and the reason of it was, because Mistress <hi>Cumber,</hi> Wife to the former Master of that Colledge, did, about twenty years ago, out of great Piety, Zeal, and Devotion, secretly convey away this Altar, with all its appurtenances, that it might escape those most Sacrilegious hands, which at that time did both in <hi>Cambridge,</hi> and every where else, destroy those Sacred Shrines, as Badges of Superstition, and Introductions to Popery. But by the care and diligence of this holy Matron (whose merits by reason thereof, may justly challenge, upon the full and plenary resti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of Holy Church, an advancement to the place of <hi>Lady Abbess</hi> at least in the best Monastry in <hi>England</hi>) this Altar was preserved in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire till <hi>these</hi> dayes of <hi>Reformation</hi> (wherein we are as far from Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery, as Purgatory is from Hell) and so the whole frame of it being ready fixed, it was immediately set up, and became the Copy for all other Colledges to write after. This Circumstance in the case, hath administred much matter to the <hi>Phannatick</hi> small-Beer-Wits in the University to work upon, who do from hence most inconsequently argue, that if the <hi>MOTHER-ALTAR,</hi> and that too in a <hi>Royal</hi> Foundation, which had out-lived so many years of Sacriledge, could not now at last escape the Rage of Prophane Fire; then the same or a worse Fate is like to attend all the Daughters. A Coal from this Altar may probably fire the whole Nest of them.<hi>Proximus ardet Ucaligon.</hi>But others, who are greater Friends to Devotion, and the Propagating of our speedy Return into the bosome of our <hi>dear Mother beyond Sea,</hi> than these cock-brain'd <hi>Phannaticks</hi> are, do judge it very convenient, that upon this sad occasion, our Learned Convocation do enter into a speedy and grave Debate, whether it be not necessary (to prevent the spreading of this Fire any further) that <hi>this</hi> or a like Form of Deprecation be forth-with added to the <hi>Letany</hi> lately Established by Act of <hi>Parliament,</hi> viz.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>From Snuffs in the Quire,</l>
                  <l>From unhallowed Fire,</l>
                  <l>From Candles Ends,</l>
                  <l>And from seeming Friends,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Libera nos,</hi> &amp;c.</l>
               </q>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="conclusion">
            <pb facs="tcp:55733:31"/>
            <head>The CONCLUSION.</head>
            <p>THus we have at last, though through many difficulties (in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of the watchful eye that is continually upon the <hi>Press</hi>) dispatched this <hi>Second Part</hi> also, which is swelled much bigger than we expected, though not beyond that true and satisfactory account, which we have received concerning the Particulars, which we are confident will appear <hi>so</hi> to the most Critical (if impartial) exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of them. If any thing of like nature hereafter occur, we shall as the Lord gives opportunity, make it publick also. In the mean time, let us consider <hi>these,</hi> and endeavour to improve them to a spee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Repentance, and continual Watchfulness, <hi>for we know not in what hour our Lord will come.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:55733:31"/>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>